<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/nonprofit-strategy/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>Your Disaster Response Plan</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Hurricane Season is around the corner (the official start is June 1), and while <a href="http://www.heraldtribune.com/news/20180518/experts-hurricane-season-may-be-less-active-than-first-predicted">some experts</a> report that it won’t be as brutal as in recent years, it never hurts to revisit some tried and true practices that could help you and your organization avoid headaches, save a lot of time, and be ready to spring into action when the time comes.</p>

<p>When I was working at nonprofits, I’d often fall into the same trap every year: I’d be so focused on the calendar and the next campaign that we needed to send out, then get blindsided by a sudden onslaught of  calls from donors wondering what we were going to do to help people on the ground of the latest natural disaster. That’s where I’d like to start with all of this: Is your organization perceived as one that should provide services to those in need in emergency situations? If you, your colleagues, or your ED can’t answer that question, you need to figure it out…because you don’t want to be on the receiving end of a call, stammering and unsure of how to respond to a donor who is simply saying “take my money.”</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Fry.jpg" alt="Take My Money" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>The phrase any fundraiser loves to hear.</span></p>

<p>Let’s say you’ve decided you are the type of organization that will be sending a response team or will be funneling dollars to other local agencies where disaster has struck. Set up your unique tracking and fund codes to ensure those dollars don’t mix with your general operating bucket. The reason I say this is because disaster donors are, by and large, the one night stands of fundraising. We love them, but maybe they don’t love us as much to be in a long-term relationship – and that’s ok! Although, I have witnessed some exceptions to that rule (<a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/12/is-november-2016-and-outlier-or-the-new-normal/">see November 2016, post election behavior</a>), it’s rare to see a ladder of engagement where someone’s first gift was for emergency relief and, low and behold, 3 weeks later they’re a monthly donor.</p>

<p>Blackbaud (whether you love em or love to hate em) has also done some <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/giving-when-disaster-strikes_us_59c0e106e4b0c3e70e742793">research</a> that elaborates on the lack of stickiness with disaster donors. Ultimately, you don’t want that swell in donations to mislead you when you’re planning your budget and setting goals for the following year. Keep it separated.</p>

<h3 id="the-checklist">The checklist:</h3>

<p><strong>Bandwidth</strong></p>

<p>The majority of fundraising tends to happen in the <a href="https://www.networkforgood.com/nonprofitblog/infographic-disaster-strikes-america-gives/">two weeks</a> after an episodic event takes place. Knowing that, how does your organization need to prepare? Do you need to set up a phone bank to handle an increase in calls? Is your website able to handle a spike in traffic of Hulk-like proportions? I’ll be honest, I still have nightmares of websites going down the last week of the year due to the volume of site visitors overloading us. You don’t want that happening at peak fundraising time (or anytime, for that matter). Luckily technology has come a long way in the last 10-ish years and many of us don’t have to worry about this as much. But it’s a good idea to check yourself, before you wreck yourself.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/hulk.jpg" alt="The Hulk" /></p>

<p><strong>Speed</strong></p>

<p>Can your site load in under 2 seconds? Because that’s the expectation users have now.  M+R dedicated an entire section of their <a href="https://mrbenchmarks.com/#!/speed">2018 Benchmarks study</a> to speed, saying that “a one-second delay in page load time can lead to an 11% decrease in traffic, and significantly fewer conversions.” Make sure you’re taking steps now to improve the experience when it will matter most. This isn’t just a disaster response plan, it should be the standard.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/theflash.jpg" alt="The Flash" /></p>

<p><strong>The Messaging</strong></p>

<p>Adjusting the communication plan was always the most jarring for me; because I already had a plan, but I had to pitch it all and start over (I love a roadmap, but despise forced improvisation)! Taking small steps to prepare now will help minimize the stress of having to create a bunch of new pieces overnight to solicit support later.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/messaging.jpg" alt="Coffee cup with inspirational message" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Create a template. By that I don’t mean “create a highly designed and polished email” but have a starting point with some copy that you can easily fill in with specific details or edit once you have more information. Standard things to include might be your efficiency rating / how far a dollar goes; maybe adding in some boilerplate language about your organization and its effectiveness.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Loosely set the cadence for the messages, but be flexible so you can respond to things in the moment as the situation evolves.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Don’t forget about social media. As in, don’t forget to amplify your message there and utilize your connections, fans, and influencers to spread your message. Have a plan for how to reach out to those influencers and talk to them about the work you’re doing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Incorporate texting. I say this with caution because I’ve had bad experiences with text-to-give in the past, and it just depends on the vendor. Be sure to read all the fine print! Don’t end up like me: wondering where all the money is and realizing that the vendor only sends it to you in a lump sum every 6 months (and only if the donor has paid their phone bill). But don’t let my sour attitude get you down – there are a lot of benefits to giving via text; several are outlined in this <a href="https://trust.guidestar.org/text-to-give-software-five-unexpected-and-amazing-benefits">helpful list from Guidestar</a>. If you find a vendor that you love, add your recommendations in the comments below so we can also give em some love! And once you’ve got one lined up, agree upon the logic you’ll use to create your keywords so they’re consistent.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>All this is to say, have a checklist of things you need to do when the time comes, so that you’re not scrambling to be 5 different people at once (that may still happen, but at least you’ll be prepared)!</p>

<p><strong>On a serious note</strong></p>

<p>I’ve injected some levity into this post, but natural disasters affect real people and can set a state’s/city’s/country’s infrastructure back exponentially. As we brace for the 2018 hurricane season, we cannot ignore the massive devastation from 2017 and the thousands of people in Puerto Rico affected by Hurricane Maria (which was a mere 8 months ago). The media has moved on, but significant relief work continues, and <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/nation/puerto-ricos-recovery-7-months-after-hurricane-maria">the needs are mounting</a> and continually reassessed. If you want to do something about it, <a href="https://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=content.view&amp;cpid=5356">here are some organizations from Charity Navigator</a> that are providing relief efforts.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Your-Disaster-Response-Plan/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Your-Disaster-Response-Plan/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Preparing for the GDPR</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<h3 id="weve-recently-updated-our-privacy-policy"><strong>“We’ve recently updated our privacy policy.”</strong></h3>

<p>If you’ve ever given your email address to an online store, entity, social media platform or done just about anything online, then you’ve probably received the above notice in your inbox from those entities with increasing regularity over the last month or two.</p>

<p>Most of these notices are related to the European Union’s General Data Protection Regulations (GDPR) that are going into effect later this month on <strong>May 25, 2018.</strong></p>

<p>To be clear, <strong>we at ThinkShout are not lawyers</strong> and we strongly encourage our clients and anyone collecting user information in some way, shape, or form to seek legal counsel for your own specific obligations related to the GDPR. Here’s how we’re viewing the regulations and what actions we are taking at ThinkShout.</p>

<h3 id="the-big-picture">The big picture</h3>

<p>The regulations apply specifically to organizations that collect or process data associated with EU citizens. The overall intent is to give EU citizens control over how their own data is collected and used. The stick that’s being wielded to enforce the regulations is the possibility of fines of up to €20 million or 4% of an organization’s global annual revenue (whichever is greater). Charitable organizations are not exempted from these penalties, however it’s likely that the steep fines will be for recurring or significant privacy issues and that the focus will be on fixing any issues that are discovered. There are questions about enforceability (particularly in the USA) that will likely need to be settled in court, but many of the regulations reflect smart privacy practices regardless of the penalties. All the chatter and hand wringing about the GDPR has led to a fast growing industry of businesses offering compliance audits, consulting and technical solutions to the regulations. Some of the vendors offering these services are legitimate, while many are simply designed to sell products or services based on embellished fears.</p>

<p><a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/principles/">The principles of the GDPR</a> can be broadly summed up as protecting personal data by allowing individuals to choose what data they allow to be collected, how that data is used or processed, and gives them control over that data even after it’s been collected. The UK’s Information Commissioner’s Office provides an easy to read <a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/">guide to the GDPR</a> that goes into detail on the various provisions while the EU provides a <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/justice/smedataprotect/index_en.htm">more graphical explanation</a>. That last link might be more palatable for the visual learners reading this.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/GDPR-Data.png" alt="EU Graphic Explanation of GDPR" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Portion of the EU’s graphical explanation of GDPR - full explanation can be found <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/justice/smedataprotect/index_en.htm">here</a>.</span></p>

<h3 id="does-the-gdpr-apply-to-you-and-your-users">Does the GDPR apply to you and your users?</h3>

<p>In short, probably. While compliance is technically only needed when handling data for EU citizens, discerning who is and isn’t a EU citizen can be difficult, and compliance in many cases isn’t all that cumbersome.</p>

<h3 id="documentation-and-communication-are-two-of-the-key-areas-of-responsibility">Documentation and communication are two of the key areas of responsibility.</h3>

<p>Start with an audit of the data you collect from users, the data you collect from other sources and what is done with that data. Note that this isn’t just about new data but also any data already in your various systems (website, Salesforce, spreadsheets, etc.). Once you know what user information you have and why you have it, communicate that information to both your staff and your users by updating your privacy notices, and emailing constituents with that now famous subject line, “We’ve recently updated our privacy policy.”</p>

<p>Document how your data handling processes are shared with new staff. It’s also a good idea to revise privacy policies written by lawyers to be “concise, transparent, intelligible and easily accessible” and should further be “written in clear plain language.”</p>

<p><a href="https://ico.org.uk/media/for-organisations/documents/1625136/good-and-bad-examples-of-privacy-notices.pdf">Here’s an example of good privacy notices and requests for consent.</a></p>

<p>Basically, ensure that the general population (who did not attend law school) can easily understand the language.</p>

<h3 id="processing-must-be-allowed-under-a-lawful-basis">Processing must be allowed under a lawful basis.</h3>

<p>Any processing of personal data must be supported by both the need to process that data as well as a lawful basis. Out of the <a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/lawful-basis-for-processing/">eight lawful bases</a> that the GDPR defines, consent, legal obligation and legitimate interest appear to be the most likely to be cited in the work of our clients. For consent to apply, it must be active (opt-in), current, specific and revocable.</p>

<p>Legal obligation covers data needed for accounting or other legal audit trails. Legitimate interest is less defined, but addresses situations where the usage of the data can be reasonably expected, has minimal privacy impact and there is strong justification for the processing of the data. Using a user’s email address on an account they created to send them a link to reset their password might be an example of legitimate interest as a lawful basis.</p>

<h3 id="individuals-have-defined-rights-to-the-protection-and-usage-of-their-data">Individuals have defined rights to the protection and usage of their data.</h3>

<ol>
  <li>The right to be informed: privacy notices, accurate opt-in information, etc.</li>
  <li>The right of access: ability to see any data you have on an individual.</li>
  <li>The right to rectification: ability to correct any errors in the data you have - allowing users to update their own profiles covers much of this right.</li>
  <li>The right to erasure: ability to request data be removed. This is not all encompassing, nor does it need to be automated. Data needed for legal or other legitimate needs can be retained.</li>
  <li>The right to restrict processing: ability to request that their data not be processed but also not deleted.</li>
  <li>The right to data portability: ability to request a machine readable export of their data.</li>
  <li>The right to object: ability to opt out of marketing, processing based on legitimate interest or processing for research or statistical purposes. The process for opting out must be clearly explained in the privacy notice and at the point of first communication.</li>
  <li>Rights in relation to automated decision making and profiling: If you collect data to profile individuals for behavior tracking or marketing purposes then <a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/individual-rights/rights-related-to-automated-decision-making-including-profiling/">additional regulations apply.</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="what-about-cookies">What about cookies?</h3>

<p>Cookies aren’t specifically called out in the GDPR, however some of the provisions can apply to them. Some experts recommend altering the site behavior to prevent cookies from being created until after the user has provided and the site has recorded consent. <a href="https://www.civicuk.com/cookie-control">Several</a> <a href="https://www.cookiebot.com/en/">services</a> seek to provide paid services that support this approach, although altering the code on your site is generally necessary to use them correctly. A few Drupal modules and WordPress plugins also seek to provide this functionality. It is expected that in 2019 the <a href="https://www.i-scoop.eu/gdpr/eu-eprivacy-regulation/#The_EU_ePrivacy_Regulation_and_cookies">revised e-Privacy Directive</a> will shift some or all of the obligations for managing consent related to cookies to the browser application.</p>

<h3 id="recommendations">Recommendations</h3>

<p>We’re recommending that all our clients take the following steps to ensure compliance:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Evaluate your organization’s legal needs related to the GDPR. Consulting with your own counsel is recommended.</li>
  <li>Appoint an internal person to take responsibility for data protection in your organization. While the GDPR includes provisions for <a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/accountability-and-governance/data-protection-officers/">appointing a Data Protection Officer (DPO)</a>, it’s specifically for public authorities and organizations whose core business is tracking behavior or processing criminal data. Appointing a staff person will help avoid a diffusion of responsibility regarding data security.</li>
  <li>Audit your data collection and processing <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1fEys1ekOpHjup2l9Jto-Q8Ppv8P96jezou2kkOu9PcU/edit#gid=0">(here’s a sample template)</a>:
    <ul>
      <li>What is being held already and what is being collected?</li>
      <li>Is there data being collected or stored that isn’t needed?</li>
      <li>How is the collected data is used within the organization?</li>
      <li>Is there a legal basis for the different pieces of personal data being collected?</li>
      <li>If consent is the legal basis, is the consent active (opt-in), granular and recent?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Review and revise privacy notices and cookie policies to be clearly written and comprehensive. Be sure to include information about third-party data collection (Google Analytics, AddThis, Facebook, etc). <a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-data-protection/privacy-notices-transparency-and-control/your-privacy-notice-checklist/">Here’s a privacy notice checklist to get you started.</a></li>
  <li>Document processes for handling user requests as well as security breaches. Your organization has a month to respond to an individual’s request for export, access, or deletion of their data. In most cases this will currently be a manual process although there is working happening in both the Drupal and WordPress communities to make these request easier to accommodate. If there is a data breach, the GDPR states that the regulating agency must be notified within 72-hours. A good starting point is the <a href="https://iapp.org/resources/article/security-breach-response-plan-toolkit/">Security Breach Response Plan Toolkit.</a></li>
  <li>Evaluate if changes to your website (beyond the privacy/cookie notices) are necessary. Consider specifically:
    <ul>
      <li>Is Google Analytics configured properly? Ensure IP anonymization is enabled, data retention settings are correct and that no personal information is being tracked (check page urls, titles, etc.).</li>
      <li>What third-party scripts or pixel trackers are included?</li>
      <li>How is consent being collected in newsletter signup forms?</li>
      <li>How is consent being collected in user registration forms?</li>
      <li>Any other places that user data could be collected?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="whats-next-for-us">What’s next for us?</h3>

<p>Like most agencies, we’re continuing to learn more about the GDPR and the implications for our clients. We are working in partnership with them to help them understand and implement changes that might be needed on their sites or their internal processes. Internally we’re providing additional training on the principles of <a href="https://www.ryerson.ca/pbdce/certification/seven-foundational-principles-of-privacy-by-design/">privacy by design</a> to our team. In terms of our open source work we’ll be incorporating <a href="http://eepurl.com/dqP8Bb">MailChimp’s GDPR consent forms</a> into the <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/mailchimp">Drupal MailChimp modules</a> as soon as the functionality is available in their API. We see opportunities for including functionality related to subject access requests (export, deletion, etc) and consent tracking in our RedHen CRM suite of modules as well.</p>

<p>Bottom line is: this is something we all need to be cognizant of; it’s not solely an EU issue. We’ll continue to keep a close eye on this as GDPR gets rolled out – and there are many resources out there at your disposal (and within this blog post). You can be sure to get the latest from us on this and other digital trends by <a href="https://thinkshout.com/contact/">signing up for our newsletter</a> and following us on <a href="https://twitter.com/ThinkShout">twitter</a>. Good luck!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Making-GDPR-Preparations/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Making-GDPR-Preparations/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>How to Run a Landscape Analysis</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>No organization is an island. While each and every mission-driven organization is unique, many aspects of your work are shared by other organizations. Having similar goals, objectives, and core audiences can make it difficult to know how to stand out. One of the most efficient and cost-saving ways to gain such insight is by understanding and navigating the landscape you operate in.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-a-landscape-analysis">What is a Landscape Analysis?</h3>
<p>Basically, a landscape analysis allows you to learn about your competitor landscape:</p>

<p>Who else is in your sector and doing what you do or want to do? What are they doing well? Where do they fall short (and subsequently, where can you fulfill a need)? What isn’t being done at all?</p>

<p>All of these questions can be answered by a landscape analysis. The process breaks down into three steps, which we explore in more depth later on:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Identification</strong> of key organizations in a field, sector, or location</li>
  <li><strong>Classification</strong> of those organizations by relevant characteristics (organization type, target audience, mission)</li>
  <li><strong>Evaluation</strong> of how they’re performing relative to the focus of your review</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="why-is-it-important">Why is it important?</h3>
<p>A better understanding of the broader context in which you are operating can help you design your strategy to maximize your impact. Some benefits can be:</p>

<p><strong>Saving Time &amp; Money</strong></p>

<p>Research can often be an under-resourced line item in a mission-driven organization’s budget. But the upfront investment into a landscape analysis can pay dividends over time by helping avoid problems you might otherwise face, and ensure your offerings are the most effective and unique to grab your audience’s attention and achieve your organizational goals.</p>

<p><strong>Innovating and Improving</strong></p>

<p>Seeing how others are providing a similar offering often sparks creative ideas on your team for how to improve and/or innovate the work.</p>

<p><strong>Making Actionable Decisions</strong></p>

<p>Stuck on how best to move forward or improve your offerings? Knowing what others are doing can help dislodge any of that and bring action items more clearly into focus.</p>

<p><strong>Identifying Opportunities</strong></p>

<p>Differentiating your organization from others in the space is key to success, and a landscape review allows you to identify those areas where you can either outperform others or fill a gap that no one is filling yet. You can quickly get up to speed on everything from a new field to a new geographic focus, from new trends to not-yet identified competitors.</p>

<p>This was where one of our most recent projects with <a href="https://anitab.org/">AnitaB.org</a> took us.</p>

<p>AnitaB.org is on a mission to connect, inspire, and guide women in computing and organizations that view technology innovation as a strategic imperative. The organization supports women working in technical fields, as well as the companies that employ them and the academic institutions that educate them. Each year AnitaB.org hosts the <a href="https://ghc.anitab.org/">Grace Hopper Celebration</a>, a three-day event which draws over 18,000 women together, and it serves as one of the most powerful ways AnitaB.org carries out its mission.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/GHC_2018.jpg" alt="GHC 2018" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Natania and Mimi attended GHC as part of ThinkShout’s research and introduction to <a href="https://anitab.org/">AnitaB.org</a>.</span></p>

<p>They approached ThinkShout with the goal to provide the same kind of powerful experience and support to women in technology a full 365 days a year, and not just the three days of the Grace Hopper Celebration. Our assignment was to research whether any organization was already providing this kind of support and a sense of community to women in tech, and to also identify online platforms that deliver similar support to their users in unique and innovative ways.</p>

<h3 id="how-do-you-do-a-landscape-analysis">How do you do a landscape analysis?</h3>

<p><strong>1. Understand You, Your Goals, and Everyone You Want to Engage</strong></p>

<p>The first step is to be clear about your organizational goals, your target audiences, and what those audiences are looking for. This will ensure that you ask the right questions in your analysis and end up with accurate insights. If you haven’t done so before, conducting user research may help uncover what your audiences really need that they are not currently getting, and can also be great preliminary research into the organizations to include in your landscape analysis (keep an eye out for a future blog post about that!).</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Mimi_Chelsea_Posts.jpg" alt="Evaluating features" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Mimi and Chelsea sorted through features to determine how they related to the client/project goals.</span></p>

<p>For AnitaB.org, we actually started out organizing our thinking around the kind of concrete features that would comprise an online engagement platform — a user’s profile, private messaging and groups, and event functionality, for example. But we stepped back and re-oriented our goal to something that was bigger picture and much more specific to our client’s particular needs: how do we connect women meaningfully and help them advance in their career and as advocates for women in tech via an online platform?</p>

<p><strong>2. Set Parameters</strong></p>

<p>Once you have your goals in hand, you want to determine the parameters, or the criteria, of your analysis: who do you include? Who do you not? You may want to consider:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Whether organization type matters</li>
  <li>Where there is issue area or mission overlap</li>
  <li>Whether to set a narrow set of parameters within a broad context, or a broad set of parameters within a narrow context</li>
</ul>

<p>For AnitaB.org, we set a narrow set of parameters within a broad context. We chose to seek out organizations who were meeting their own goals well — these were by and large not the same goals as our client’s — but who did so using similar strategies to AnitaB.org: facilitating connections between people who may otherwise not meet, and providing opportunities for mentorship, professional development, and career advancement.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/WOC_tech_chat.jpg" alt="Women in Tech" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Photo credit: #WOCinTech Chat on <a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/wocintechchat/">Flickr</a></span></p>

<p><em>Quick Tip: It may be tempting to skip the first two steps and jump right into step 3, but how can you find what you’re looking for if you don’t know what you’re trying to find? A bit more time upfront will result in more efficient research results and outcomes from your analysis.</em></p>

<p><strong>3. Brainstorm &amp; Vet Potential Organizations</strong></p>

<p>Now that you know what you are looking for, go out and think about every organization that might fit your criteria here! This isn’t the editing stage — that comes next — so be as creative as you can while brainstorming which organizations might fit your criteria. Then, spend a brief time reviewing each one against your parameters, and see how they stack up against each other.</p>

<p>ThinkShout created a list of over 20 organizations that fit our client’s parameters, and it was a diverse list: no two organizations were delivering the same product, but they all had common aspects to their work that mapped back to our goals for our client. We spent about an hour exploring each one and ranking how well it performed against our criteria. Those that ranked highest moved forward in our analysis.</p>

<p><em>Quick Tip: If you are improving or evolving current offerings, be sure to include your own organization in the next step!</em></p>

<p><strong>4. Examine Strengths, Weaknesses, and Opportunities of Select Organizations</strong></p>

<p>Time and budget typically don’t allow for a full in-depth analysis of more than a handful of organizations. But you can still get a lot of value of doing a deep dive into those select few. Spend a while longer getting to know your top-ranked organizations, and really uncover those areas where they’re performing well and not so well. An analysis across your select organizations may reveal those opportunities where no one is currently providing any offerings.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/anita-b-landscape-analysis.jpg" alt="landscape analysis" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Some platforms we included were Italki, NTEN, and Doximity.</span></p>

<p>At this stage of our client project, we had six platforms that we each spent an additional three hours of time on; getting to know how they facilitated new connections between their users, connected mentors with mentees, delivered professional development content, and promoted career opportunities. In doing so, we came away with many valuable insights that informed the development of the final phase of our project, creating a recommended set of core features for a new online platform. Those insights included:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Unique and specific features AnitaB.org could take inspiration from to build their own platform,</li>
  <li>Offerings that were so strongly provided by other organizations that it didn’t make sense for our client to invest resources in developing and trying to compete against, and</li>
  <li>A confirmation of market opportunity.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="what-could-a-landscape-analysis-do-for-you">What Could a Landscape Analysis Do For You?</h3>
<p>Whether it’s a new website, program, or offering that you’re considering, you don’t want to invest resources in something that someone else is already doing so well that you have no chance to compete with them. On the flip side, if you want to venture into an area that many have struggled with, you want to know what they’ve tried so you can learn their lessons and avoid their same mistakes. After all, your mission, at the end of the day, is at stake. You want to maximize your impact while minimizing cost. A little research in the short-term will go far in ensuring the long-term success of your efforts.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/high_five.gif" alt="SUCCESS" /></p>

<h3 id="thinkshout-is-here-to-help">ThinkShout is Here to Help</h3>
<p>Are you considering a landscape analysis for your organization but not sure if you have the bandwidth to take on the work? We’d love to help you! Our team is comprised of former nonprofit staff and agency veterans who have decades of experience working with nonprofits that vary in size, budgets, and goals, so we know what it’s like to be in your shoes. We are here to help you achieve your goals and be your strategic partner. To get started, <a href="https://thinkshout.com/contact/">let us know a little more about your needs.</a></p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Landscape-Analysis/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Landscape-Analysis/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
