<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/donor-retention/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>Is November 2016 an Outlier or the New Normal?</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>For many, this election cycle and the subsequent aftermath has been a rather unsettling, tumultuous experience. I’m still processing and mapping out what’s next and where to focus my personal resources – but in the nonprofit space, there has already been much conjecture about what this new administration will mean for the industry.</p>

<p>David Callahan wrote up some thoughts for <a href="http://www.insidephilanthropy.com/home/2016/11/9/philanthropy-in-the-age-of-trump-five-predictions">Inside Philanthropy</a>, and among his predictions he listed philanthropy influencing society more and centrist donors rallying to save what they value in society. He states, “we’ll see a wave of funder-backed initiatives aimed at bringing more civility and unity to public life.”</p>

<p>It’s only been a couple weeks, but some of those predictions are coming to fruition.</p>

<p>There has been an immediate urge from half of the country to do something to counter the results. And many spoke with their wallets for causes they want to preserve in a world of unknowns.</p>

<p>In the days following November 8th, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2016/11/donald-trump-donations/507668/">individuals came out in droves</a> to fiscally support organizations that serve society’s vulnerable and disenfranchised citizens. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/18/us/politics/nonprofit-donations-trump.html?_r=0">Environmental groups saw a spike as well</a>, since our president-elect <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/pictures/wild-donald-trump-quotes/13/">has said things</a> that indicate he does not view climate change as an issue that warrants action.</p>

<p>For several organizations, the spikes in website traffic and donations in the days following the election exceeded totals from December 31st. If you’re up on your fundraising trivia, you know that’s practically unheard of, save for the instance in which giving swells after a natural disaster.</p>

<p>In fact, this recent surge in philanthropic giving looks similar to that of disaster giving. It’s a clarion call. People felt - and continue to feel - a need to take action and harness control in a world that presents them with so many uncertainties.</p>

<p>Personally, I signed up as a monthly donor to two organizations post-election, and already their autoresponders reflect timely messaging, including what their needs will be moving forward. This immediacy to respond in a way that lines up with my motivations wasn’t just good planning and foresight, it is the new norm and the expectation many users have when they invest money in a cause.</p>

<p>The question is, will this surge in giving follow the model of disaster relief and begin to peter out, or has it become the new normal for a least the next few years? How this new wave of supporters gets treated - how you thank them for their support and engage with them moving forward - could impact their commitment for years to come. How can you keep that charitable fire alive in your hundreds of brand new donors and incite them to action in the future?</p>

<p>Here’s what we’d suggest as a start:</p>

<p><strong>On-boarding</strong>. These new donors deserve more than an autoresponder before getting folded into your normal communication stream. Use a welcome series to let them know that you will not let them down, share the ways you will put their dollars to work, and highlight additional ways they can get involved in your mission. Offer opportunities for volunteering, or ways they can get involved at the local v. national level. Provide tangible ways they can take action to feel they are active participants and not just a checkbook to you.</p>

<p><strong>Communicate with them.</strong> Just like in any relationship, communication is key. Now more than ever, in part due to the degradation of truth during the election, people are fact-checking and they want to know that you are using funds efficiently. So tell them. Include links to your <a href="http://www.charitynavigator.org/">Charity Navigator</a> profile for full transparency. Send updates where the sole purpose is to report back on what has been accomplished. Nothing makes the donor experience more unsatisfactory than giving to an organization that never closes the loop with you. If you meet a goal, let your new supporters know. If you pass a major milestone for an advocacy effort, let them know. People want to be part of a story, and lack of communication is a leading cause for disengagement. Assume that everyone who donates in the early stages of your campaign wants to know the impact of their gift, regardless of whether that happens months, or even years later. You have more to lose by not sharing this news with them, regardless of how long it takes for your campaign to come full circle.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t be afraid to ask.</strong> Monthly donors are the holy grail of supporters for nonprofits. This type of giving makes it easier for organizations to budget when unexpected expenses arise or funding gets cut. So make a strong case for ongoing support and share the long-term impact that it has on your organization and the communities you serve. <a href="https://www.nrdc.org/">Some organizations</a> are making monthly giving the focus of their call to action on their site and deploying lightboxes/pop-ups to promote it. This is the exact situation where a lightbox makes sense: it’s timely and relevant to something happening in our lives. People feel motivated to help <em>right now</em> and monthly giving is the most effective way to support missions that matter to them.</p>

<p><strong>Thank them.</strong> While telling supporters all the wonderful ways you are working towards making a positive impact is great, it’s ultimately all possible because of them, and they need to know that. This extends beyond personalizing that autoresponder – emails get deleted in a swipe – but consider supplementing that autoresponder with a mailed thank-you note (or test it on a small subset of your file, anyway). Some <a href="http://www.thenonprofittimes.com/management-tips/channels-equal-revenue/">data suggests</a> that contacting donors through more than one media channel increases giving levels. It can go a long way.</p>

<p>There is no silver bullet for <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/05/roadmap-to-retention/">donor retention</a>, but one way to avoid losing these first time/renewed supporters is to engage with them and make them part of the conversation. Offer ways for everyone to participate, either virtually or on the ground. Individuals are looking for what’s next, what can they do to help, and how they can be a part of the solution. Everyone is listening. How are you going to show up for them?</p>

<p>It’s hard to say at this point what we will make of November 2016, whether it will be a statistical anomaly that we exclude in future budget planning, or whether it will be the new norm. Election aside, I hope that you take these principles and reexamine what you have planned for year-end. Tweak the messaging to reflect the new landscape as needed. Determine if your social strategy needs to be revised. Take steps to make your supporters feel more included and part of the narrative. I don’t have any concrete answers. I don’t think any of us will for a while. What I do have is a strong desire to see us all succeed.</p>

<p>At ThinkShout, we are fortunate to be able to help many causes doing important, valuable work on behalf of those in our society that need it the most. My hope is that you can take some of the recommendations I’ve shared and put them to use to help elevate your engagements with your audiences and take your messages even further, for the betterment of the world we all share.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/12/is-november-2016-and-outlier-or-the-new-normal/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/12/is-november-2016-and-outlier-or-the-new-normal/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Roadmap to Retention</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>We’ve talked about <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/03/rethinking-strategies-for-online-donor-acquisition/">ways to attract and on-board new supporters</a>. Maybe you’ve started testing some of those strategies and set up a lightbox. That was a lot of hard work! Let’s take a break…</p>

<p>… and talk about how to cultivate those newbies so they don’t abandon ship. It’s called the <a href="http://www.pamelagrow.com/7256/are-you-taking-advantage-of-the-honeymoon-phase-in-your-nonprofit-marketing/">honeymoon phase</a>, and you need to take advantage of it while those contacts are feeling warm and fuzzy about supporting you.</p>

<p>Let’s back up a few steps. Think about the people in your life. You have tertiary contacts - people that are friends of friends, or vague acquaintances that you might see at a party and never again. Then, there are closer contacts – maybe they’re coworkers or people from class. You know them on the surface; some of their hobbies, general interests. You might even connect with them on LinkedIn, maybe Facebook. Then there are our closer friends; these are individuals you have a phone number and personal email for. They aren’t blocked from any of your social media accounts and you text each other frequently. You know each other on a deeper level and rarely find cause for disagreement.</p>

<p>This isn’t an exact parallel to the donor-relationship, but you get the idea. You want that donor to be happy to hear from you and for there to be a mutual appreciation. How can you create that type of relationship and feeling in this new contact?</p>

<p>Spoiler alert: there’s no ultimate, magic solution. You have to test and see what works for your audience. This won’t be the last time you hear me say this, either. The only way to determine what works is to fail early and often… until you don’t. The only way to do that is to test.</p>

<p>What we can do however is provide some basic guidance and make recommendations based on what we in the fundraising community have seen work for us.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Content: Keep it fresh and up to date on your website - give people a reason to keep coming back to you. This isn’t just of benefit to donors, by the way – refreshing content is good for Google crawlers. They’re responsible for presenting the best content in search results to end users. If your site or home page hasn’t been refreshed in some time, Google may not give you top billing in the search results. There’s a lot more that goes into SEO, but that’s a topic for another time. Bottom line is, don’t let things get stale.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It’s like the theme from the Golden Girls, “Thank you for being a friend” er, donor: Set up a stewardship series to be sure you thank your supporters for being awesome. You can’t do the vital work for your cause without them, so show your appreciation! All this money you’ve been asking people for is presumably going towards something good and valuable, share those successes – and make your donors the star.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Know your audience: Give them every opportunity to engage with you in the way(s) they want on the platforms they choose. You know your audience best (if not, we need to have a talk about that). If your file is comprised of an older demographic, you may want to hold off on a major investment in a social media push. Alternatively, if you have a younger audience of advocates, they might be more interested in events and ways they can actively participate with your cause online. Again: Know your audience.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Track your results: look for patterns (or direct feedback from contacts) in communication preferences. Monitor what gets the best responses as well as what doesn’t so you know what to repeat (or avoid) in the future, and build off those successes.</li>
  <li>Basically, maintain contact in valuable, meaningful ways. The major reason why people stop supporting an organization, outside of death or changes to one’s financial situation, is due to poor communication. <a href="https://i0.wp.com/fundraisingcoach.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/GuestPost-Jay-Love-Why-Donors-Stop-Their-Support.png">This infographic</a> from Bloomerang is a couple years old, but still highly relevant:</li>
</ul>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/retention-info.png" alt="retention-info.png" /></p>

<p>Here are the top reasons why you’re really losing donors:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Thought the charity did not need them - 5%</li>
  <li>No information on how monies were used - 8%</li>
  <li>No memory of supporting - 9%</li>
  <li>Never thanked for donating - 13%</li>
  <li>Poor service or communication - 18%</li>
</ol>

<p>The good news? It’s totally within your control to make sure you don’t succumb to these pitfalls. Unsure of where to start with your content curation or how to create an editorial calendar everyone in your organization can use? The Lightbox Collaborative has put together a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/15jQdv2ITgbUjUZ7U9i2ZEH30aiNiBk95RzX4arE4rAw/edit#gid=0">workbook</a> that’s a great starting point. Still not sure what to make of all of this? We can help – contact us to learn more about our strategic offerings and how we can put you on the roadmap to retention.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/05/roadmap-to-retention/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/05/roadmap-to-retention/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Rethinking Strategies for Online Donor Acquisition</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>File attrition is (unfortunately) a completely normal part of nonprofit life, and list churn – aka attrition or loss of subscribers/donors – happens to even the most seasoned cultivation programs. On average, organizations see a monthly churn rate of <a href="http://www.mrbenchmarks.com/" target="_blank">1.7%</a>. That’s why you must create additional opportunities to grow your file and bring more supporters on board.</p>

<p>Some online approaches have been around for a while, some are relatively new, and lastly (but certainly not least) there are some you’d be better off without.</p>

<p>Before we get to the good stuff, it’s important to note that if you want to grow your file, you need to have systems in place to properly welcome these new contacts. You wouldn’t welcome a guest to your home and neglect to show them where the restroom is or where you keep your coffee cups, right? The same goes for new email addresses: you wouldn’t drop them into the communication stream with your next newsletter or fundraising appeal… and it isn’t the way online audiences expect you to interact with them today.</p>

<p>At minimum, prepare an autoresponder message to confirm the user’s registration.</p>

<p>Want to take it a step further? Set up a <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/NonprofitWebinars/the-power-of-the-welcome-series" target="_blank">Welcome Series</a> and go into greater detail about what the user can expect to learn and receive from your organization.</p>

<p>Now, onto the nitty gritty:</p>

<h3 id="google-adwords">Google AdWords</h3>

<p>If you don’t have a <a href="https://www.google.com/intl/ALL/grants" target="_blank">Google Grant</a>, apply for one today (seriously, right after you finish reading this article). Through Google for Nonprofits, you can apply for an Ad Grant that is essentially $10k in in-kind dollars you can use towards advertising on Google.</p>

<p>There are limitations to this advertising method: Ads are text-based, and because of the cap on the cost per click (CPC) there will be some keywords you may not be able to utilize. But overall, it’s an incredible resource available to your organization <a href="https://support.google.com/nonprofits/answer/3215869?hl=en-CA&amp;ref_topic=3247288" target="_blank">if it’s a qualifying 501(c)(3)</a>.</p>

<p>If closely monitored and executed, your organization will gain prime positioning in the search results when people type in a keyword related to your organization. It’s free advertising dollars available to you each month, and well worth the time.</p>

<h3 id="banner-ads">Banner Ads</h3>

<p>The utilization of banner ads and remarketing is growing in popularity (and necessity). In fact, the <a href="http://www.mrbenchmarks.com/" target="_blank"> 2015 Benchmarks Report </a> found that 50% of the organizations surveyed invested in some form of retargeting, while 66% invested in text/display ads. There is definitely stiff competition for visibility and getting your cause in front of the eyes of potential supporters.</p>

<p>So what is retargeting? Well, you’ve most likely experienced it already.  You’re shopping on Amazon, minding your own business, but you decide not to buy those Marc Jacobs shoes today. Before you know it, you’re killing time on Facebook at lunch and you see an ad for those shoes off to the side with those other, creepily relevant ads. Slowly, those shoes become peppered into your online experience wherever you go. This somewhat annoying but effective tactic is called remarketing.</p>

<p>And nonprofits do it, too, with <a href="http://www.nonprofitpro.com/article/finding-your-direct-mail-fundraising-donors-online/2/" target="_blank"> varying degrees of success</a>.</p>

<p>Just as you want to sync your direct mail and online marketing pieces, display ads and remarketing can help to further saturate your potential supporters and convince them to join your cause. Besides, the majority of first time visitors to your site won’t make a gift. Retargeting gives them the opportunity to come back and remedy that mistake(!) –and also helps boost brand recognition.</p>

<h3 id="social-advertising">Social Advertising</h3>

<p>You can also extend retargeting into social channels.</p>

<p>Personally, I think the verdict is still out on fundraising through social media. It is, at best, a reinforcement channel and an opportunity for additional engagement. As an acquisition channel, however, people who follow your cause on social outlets are, typically, warm prospects (if they aren’t already diligent supporters). Those relationships are important to maintain.</p>

<p>Providing quality content that an end user will want to engage with is of utmost importance – but giving them a reason to leave Facebook and go to your website is tantamount to the holy grail.</p>

<p>If you can determine what your audience identifies as high-value content, and only make said content available behind the wall of an email address exchange, you may be able to grow that file in no time.</p>

<p>Another common approach is a pledge call-to-action. I don’t mean pledge in the monetary sense; rather “sign our pledge to end hunger” or “sign our pledge to find a cure for X.” (Ideally, this action would also be tied to social sharing opportunities so that your new supporter can recruit on your behalf). The supporter “signs” the pledge by entering their email address.</p>

<p>There are also benefits to tossing some advertising dollars toward promoted posts on Facebook. Check out how <a href="http://www.networkforgood.com/nonprofitblog/heres-the-best-way-to-fundraise-on-facebook/?utm_source=feedblitz&amp;utm_medium=FeedBlitzRss&amp;utm_campaign=katyasnon-profitmarketingblog" target="_blank"> Healing Waters</a> improved their results for #GivingTuesday with minimum fuss.</p>

<p>If you get the timing right, and know the type of content your audience is likely to engage with, you can increase your brand awareness while growing your file.</p>

<h3 id="lightboxslide-in-aka-a-popup">Lightbox/Slide-In (AKA a popup)</h3>

<p>The general reaction I get when I suggest implementing a lightbox/popup as a means to collect names or donations is for everyone in the room to recoil in horror. But if deployed strategically and when it makes sense, site visitors won’t have an adverse reaction to it. In fact, they’ll be glad you made it easier for them to find what they’re looking for.</p>

<p>You can deploy a lightbox with email signup fields on your homepage. Or, with some minimal sleuthing of your analytics data, you can identify the high-engagement pages on your site and launch a slide-in. Maybe you have a number of informative articles on disease prevention or early detection (for example). While someone is reading said article, a slide-in appears in the lower right corner: “Want to receive more vital information and updates like what you’re reading now? Sign up today.”</p>

<p>It’s all in how you position it. If you’re making their life easier, they won’t mind. But if you constantly interrupt their experience on every page, you’re more likely to receive a negative reaction. (So, don’t do that!)</p>

<p>All of the above recommendations should be paired with a Welcome Series or autoresponder once the submission form has processed. These methods all take some time to plan and deploy.</p>

<p>So, where should you not focus your energy?</p>

<h3 id="buyingrenting-email-lists">Buying/Renting Email Lists</h3>

<p>This often functions through a third party vendor, who will email (on your behalf) a file of hundreds (sometimes thousands) of emails they have identified as having an affinity to your cause. Your organization only gets the names if someone makes a gift or opts in through the vendor’s system.</p>

<p>This method is not only rather expensive, but it rarely (if ever) yields a return worth the investment. That’s not surprising: imagine how you would react to an email in your inbox that you know you didn’t sign up for… from an organization you have never heard of or been involved with. That’s an immediate swipe/delete.</p>

<p>Hubspot did a write-up on <a href="http://blog.hubspot.com/blog/tabid/6307/bid/32892/Why-Purchasing-Email-Lists-Is-Always-a-Bad-Idea.aspx" target="_blank"> why buying a list is a bad idea</a> should you need to bolster your argument to anyone who isn’t convinced.</p>

<p>So, focus on setting up the infrastructure to properly introduce new contacts into your organization, make them feel like they’re a part of something special with a welcome series. Then test, tweak, and re-test some of these methods to see what works best for you.</p>

<p>Have you tried any of these approaches to acquiring email addresses? Share with us what’s worked for you!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/03/rethinking-strategies-for-online-donor-acquisition/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/03/rethinking-strategies-for-online-donor-acquisition/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
