<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/business/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>Our Road to B Corp</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<h3 id="what-is-a-b-corp-time-for-homework">What is a B Corp? Time For Homework###</h3>

<p>Before ThinkShout, I’d never heard of a B Corp, but there it was, one of the  first projects I undertook upon my hire: “Get ThinkShout certified as a B Corp.”</p>

<p>Educating myself was step one. I watched the video “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V-VFZUFJwt4&amp;feature=youtu.be">B the Change</a>,” read the book “<a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/handbook">The B Corp Handbook</a>” by Ryan Honeyman, and combed the <a href="www.bcorporation.net">www.bcorporation.net</a> website to get a better and deeper understanding of what this movement was all about. I was blown away!</p>

<p>As stated on the site, “B Corps are certified by the nonprofit B Lab to meet rigorous standards of social and environmental performance, accountability, and transparency.” (We’ll get to the ‘rigorous’ part in a bit.) B Corp companies don’t want to be the best in the world - instead, they strive to be the best <em>for</em> the world. The change of that one word is transformative.</p>

<p>I realized how meaningful the B Corp movement is and how it would transform our company by making it a better place for our employees, a better steward of community and the environment. It’s the trifecta of awesome - there’s something for everyone and it’s all a force for positive change.</p>

<h3 id="getting-certified-capturing-the-data">Getting Certified: Capturing the Data###</h3>

<p>In order to become certified as a B Corp, there’s a rigorous ‘Assessment’ process. Think of it like the final exam in the toughest class you’ve ever taken but you <em>have</em> to pass it in order to land your dream job. On the Assessment, a score of 80 out of a potential perfect 200 is considered passing. Don’t be fooled into thinking, “Only 80?!” A lot goes into the scoring process, and data is pulled from multiple areas: Human Resources, Building Management, Purchasing, Financials, Employee Benefits . . . it’s all gathered, compiled and scored.</p>

<p>This assessment is <em>hard</em>. We’ve been in business for six years. During that time, we’ve experienced a significant amount of growth and change. Like many companies, we have policies, procedures, and values, but there wasn’t a consistent set of written procedures, or a practice of putting philosophies to paper. There was a general cultural ethos, but without it being written and <em>established</em>, we weren’t going to get points for it on the assessment.</p>

<p>The Assessment is organized into 6 parts: Governance, Workers, Community, Environment, Impact Business Models, and a Disclosure Questionnaire. I haven’t counted how many questions there are, but if you print it out, it’s 35 pages. A typical question, “What percent of full time workers have participated in external professional development opportunities or lifelong learning opportunities (paid in advance, reimbursed or subsidized by the company) in the past fiscal year?” 35 pages of questions like this and reaching a score of 80 on our first Assessment starts to feel like more of a substantial accomplishment.</p>

<p>Admittedly, it took the better part of a year to complete the Assessment, and if I had prepared better at the onset, that timeframe would have been much shorter and perhaps less stressful - although no less of an accomplishment!</p>

<h3 id="it-could-have-been-better">It Could Have Been Better###</h3>

<p>Because I was a new employee to ThinkShout, I wasn’t prepared to answer the kinds of questions required by the Assessment. By the time I put into place much of the infrastructure needed to complete the Assessment, I realized that the Assessment had already been started by my predecessor. Not knowing how she calculated some of the information was initially confusing, but it also encouraged me to dive deeper into the data. What ensued was about six months of reports, writing, and entering data into the Assessment until we were within range of the certification.</p>

<p>Now that we’re certified, I can look back and think about how I could have better prepared for this process. Take my advice:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Study the assessment before actually starting it. Read it so you know what data you’ll need to gather. Use it as the guiding blueprint or playbook.</li>
  <li>Read the book “<a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/handbook">The B Corp Handbook</a>” by Ryan Honeyman and take the guidance it offers.</li>
  <li>Make a plan. Identify the ‘pre-work’ that needs to be done. For example, if you have a mission statement <em>that is documented</em>, points are earned. If it exists but isn’t documented, no points.</li>
  <li>Identify key people. Who has the information you need? Who has the authority to make changes? Are there B Corp evangelists in the company, and are they available to help?
What does it mean to you, and to employees?</li>
</ul>

<p>Becoming a B Corp changed my relationship with ThinkShout. It gave everything I do a deeper meaning. Now, for example, when considering employee benefits, our B Corp status is part of the equation. Are we taking the welfare of our employees into consideration when we make changes? When we consider office space, we think about the location and its proximity to public transportation. We think about the energy and water usage. It reminds us of <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/">our own values</a>: when we engage with a potential new client, we think about their own mission and what change <em>they</em> are making in the world.</p>

<p>I’m proud that ThinkShout is a B Corp. When I’m talking with someone who is interested in working here, I can tell them about the B Corp certification and what it means. Almost immediately, we establish whether or not the B Corp message and mission aligns with their values.</p>

<p>Shortly after we certified and announced it to the office, a new employee shared that she’d never worked for a company that made their employees and the community such a high priority. Yeah. That is amazing.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/our-road-to-bcorp/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/our-road-to-bcorp/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Being the Change - Becoming a B Corp</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/thinkshout-bcorp-blog__2_.jpg" alt="thinkshout-bcorp.jpg" /></p>

<p>When <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2009/07/sean/why-thinkshout-why-now/">Sean</a> and <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/01/lev/levs-take-new-thinkshout-inc/">I founded</a> ThinkShout in January of 2011, one of the first things we did was sit down and write the following Mission Statement:</p>

<p><em>ThinkShout helps progressive organizations achieve their goals through web strategy and open source software. We treat our business and nonprofit clients as partners. Our motivation comes from knowing that they make the world a better place.</em></p>

<p>This Mission Statement worked well for the two of us. Our focus was 100% on our clients. We had a tiny environmental footprint, as we were just two guys with laptops and rented desks. We had no staff, so we didn’t yet need to think about organizational culture. Our considerations of the workplace environment didn’t go much further than choosing Spotify channels in our tiny office. The bottom line is that we loved using open source technology to help nonprofits have a positive impact and in our early days, our mission, as well as many other things, just <em>worked</em>.</p>

<p>In the ensuing years, we’ve been very fortunate and, well, haven’t made too much of a mess of things. We’ve connected with wonderful, forward-thinking <a href="http://thinkshout.com/work/">clients</a> who are, indeed, making the world a better place. We have a <a href="http://thinkshout.com/team/">team</a> of 21 talented, dedicated, and passionate individuals. And we’re still <a href="http://thinkshout.com/careers/">growing</a>. We have a clearly defined culture representing our values, and a gorgeous workplace to match. We laid a solid foundation for growth on top of a strong management team and cohesive organizational structure. Of course, apart from surrounding ourselves with great people, Sean and I are personally responsible for very little of all this.</p>

<h3 id="staying-focused-through-growth">Staying Focused Through Growth###</h3>

<p>As I often like to say, I have a completely new job every 6 months or so - which is a good thing. If Sean and I weren’t continually surprised, frustrated, and elated with the experience of building a company, we’d run the risk of losing our edge. New challenges are, after all, a prerequisite for new opportunities.</p>

<p>Growth brings many challenges:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Larger projects with higher stakes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A diverse team with varying work styles and needs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A more complex organizational structure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nuanced financial decisions with far reaching implications.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>To put it more succinctly, there’s just a lot more going on! Consequently, we realized that we needed to put together a better system to make sure that our growing leadership team and our overall business stays on track with our original values and goals.</p>

<p>So, we’ve made two strong investments this year. First, we embarked on a robust, 3-month strategic planning process culminating in a new missions, vision, and set of values. Second, we took the formal steps to become a “Beneficial Corporation” (or B Corp).</p>

<h3 id="our-new-vision-mission-and-values-statements">Our New Vision, Mission, and Values Statements###</h3>

<p><strong>Our Vision</strong> is to use technology and strategy to elevate organizations creating positive change in the world.</p>

<p><strong>Our Mission</strong> is to craft compelling open source engagement solutions in partnership with forward-thinking clients.</p>

<p>And our Corporate Values are the following:</p>

<p><strong>Innovation:</strong> We embrace flexibility and creativity in the approaches we take to serve our clients and staff. We recognize that our success is supported through refinement of our processes.</p>

<p><strong>Expertness:</strong> We bring proficiency and good judgement to problem solving, both internally and in serving clients. We are dedicated to being among the best at what we do, fostering a culture of continuous education and improvement.</p>

<p><strong>Respect:</strong> We respect our clients as experts in their field and honor their missions and resources. We respect the individuality and diversity of our peers. We treat each other with respect and kindness, honoring the different but equally important contributions that we all make in service to our mission.</p>

<p><strong>Helpfulness:</strong> We support the nonprofit and broader technology community through our open source contributions. We are committed to supporting our peers in their daily work and professional growth. We help organizations make the world a better place.</p>

<p><strong>Sustainability:</strong> We are committed to building a stable business that our team and clients can depend upon over time. Through our business practices, values, and client engagements, we seek to improve local communities and to have a more positive impact on the environment.</p>

<p>Circling back to our original Mission Statement at our founding, you’ll notice that at ThinkShout’s core, we hold the same values. However, our new Vision, Mission, and Values Statements provide us with a more complete framework. Specifically, they provide us with a roadmap for how we want to engage daily with our own team, our clients, and the larger world around us.</p>

<h3 id="becoming-a-certified-b-corp">Becoming a Certified B Corp###</h3>

<p>In addition to fleshing out our vision for the company, we worked hard this year to achieve <a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/community/thinkshout-inc">B Corp certification</a>. <a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/what-are-b-corps/the-non-profit-behind-b-corps">B Corp</a> represents both a framework and certification from the nonprofit B Lab, as well as a legal status in select states, with the goal of holding corporations accountable to society as well as shareholders.</p>

<p>First, we made adjustments to the company’s articles of incorporation to ensure that “benefits to society” can be prioritized over increasing shareholder wealth in making financial decisions for ThinkShout. Technically speaking, without this change, as executives of a corporation, we are legally required to prioritize shareholder value over commitment to community and the environment.</p>

<p>Second, and more importantly, B Corp certification provides us with guidelines, metrics, and a community of practice for all of the business decisions that we make in support of our team, our clients, our local community, and the environment. In other words, we now have a roadmap for continuing to make intentional choices that put people and the planet above profit.</p>

<p>Taken together, our refined mission, vision, and values, and B Corp certification give us a framework to ensure that ThinkShout stays true to its roots, and that it continues to grow. Onward and upward!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
