<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/fionta/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>That's a wrap from New Orleans!</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>It feels like it was just yesterday… probably because we still have visions of beignets dancing in our head. But we had such a blast at 18NTC, and we have you, the nonprofit community to thank for it.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/NTC Beingets.jpg" alt="Booth Beingets" /></p>

<p>Our pre-conference Drupal Day was jam-packed with content from project management to content strategy, to <a href="https://thinkshout.com/bene/">Bene</a>.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Drupal Day.jpg" alt="Drupal Day booth" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Brett and Mimi take over registration!</span></p>

<p>Here were some highlights:</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Brett - Drupal Day.jpg" alt="Content Strategy" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Brett and Chris Carrol from University of Chicago Graham School definitely schooled us (sorry) on Content Strategy in Drupal.</span></p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Lev - Drupal Day.jpg" alt="Bene" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Lev shares a case study on Bene with the crowd. Bene is an open source distribution intended for small to medium-sized nonprofits. We have a whole page dedicated to it <a href="https://thinkshout.com/bene/">here</a>.</span></p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Carie and Jess - Drupal Day.jpg" alt="Carie and Jessica talk redesign" /></p>
<p><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Jessica and Carie Lewis Carlson (formerly from the Humane Society of the United States) shared some wisdom on the challenges often faced in a redesign process.</span></p>

<p>We want to give a special shout out to our collaborators from <a href="https://www.gizra.com/">Gizra</a> and <a href="https://fionta.com/">Fionta</a> - who contributed to the breakout sessions – and to anyone who led a BOF (birds of a feather) breakout and conducted a lightning talk to close. We appreciate you adding your voice to the day.</p>

<p>Next year we’re especially excited about NTC because it’s happening right in our home town of Portland, Oregon! We’re eager to participate and contribute to the rich and vibrant nonprofit community that we deeply care about, and also show you some of what we love best about our hometown.</p>

<p>To stay up to date on everything pre-con / Drupal Day related, (or just to stay in touch!) <a href="https://thinkshout.com/contact/">sign up for our email list</a>. We’ll send a monthly newsletter with the latest trends and case studies to share…and as 19NTC approaches (too soon?) you’ll be first to hear about our plans and how you can join in the fun.</p>

<p>Below is the full agenda from Drupal Day 2018, please <a href="mailto:natania.leclerc@thinkshout.com">reach out</a> if you would like slides from any of the presentations. Thanks and see you all soon!</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Drupal Day 2018 schedule.png" alt="Drupal Day 2018 Schedule" /></p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Drupal-Day-Recap/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2018/05/Drupal-Day-Recap/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
