<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/b-corp/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>Civic Engagement at ThinkShout</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>One of the defining characteristics of the ThinkShout team is our desire to use business as a force for good. It’s what inspires the team, drives our <a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/community/thinkshout-inc">B Corp status</a>, and draws clients and partners who share our values.</p>

<p>This fall, there are many events taking place around the world that demand our attention and efforts, from the war in Syria to the drumbeat of concerns about climate change. But none, perhaps, combines the urgency and importance of the upcoming United States election, which will have a major impact on those issues and much, much, more. Luckily, unlike many of those other concerns, this one is easy to get involved in and have a direct impact.</p>

<p>ThinkShout is proud to support our team spending up to a half day on various civic engagement efforts. Some quotes and actions taken by the team:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>“I spent the afternoon with a colleague knocking on doors of registered voters. With the election right around the corner, it felt good to encourage my community to rock the vote - not only for the presidency, but down the ballot as well. It really is the boots-on-the-ground, face-to-face interactions that make all the difference during election seasons.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“I called potential volunteers for Basic Rights Oregon to help elect their endorsed candidates who all support LGBTQ rights. I really appreciated that ThinkShout made this time available for us, because it’s hard to find time to do all the volunteering I’d like to do on the evenings and weekends. This has been one of the most demoralizing elections I’ve seen, and it really helps to take action to do something positive in our local community. For the Democratic Party canvassing, I went in a group with three other ThinkShout team members, which was a great team-building experience. Everyone that I talked to, both canvassing and phone banking, was responsive and supportive. I felt like I made a difference and ThinkShout made it possible.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“I’m launching a project this week called <em>Hold Up, Bruh.</em> that encourages men to talk about and challenge behavior that leads to sexual assault. Seeing what’s become of our politics lately, I think it’s important for men specifically to take a stand on sexual harassment and sexual assault. All proceeds of the projects, which will eventually include t-shirt sales, will go directly to <a href="https://www.rainn.org/">rainn.org</a>.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“My favorite part of knocking on doors to help a political campaign is feeling more connected to my community. People seem to appreciate that you are trying to help and are enthusiastic to show their support. While Portland is full of many like-minded folks, even in more mixed political areas I’ve always found people to be friendly and happy to share their thoughts. It makes you feel proud of our democratic process and the kindness of strangers.”</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I am honored to be able to work with a group of individuals so willing to dedicate themselves to making the world a better place. The least that ThinkShout can do is stay true to its values and leverage the business to have a positive impact, however small.</p>

<p>I’ve heard it said that Democracy is a participatory sport. Go get in the game while you can!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 05:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/11/civic-engagement/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/11/civic-engagement/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Five Years</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Five years ago today, Sean and I met on the rainy steps of our attorney’s office in downtown Portland. We walked inside and proceeded to sign a small mountain of paperwork to form ThinkShout, Incorporated. Then, the two of us biked back to the 100 square foot office we’d been sharing for the previous year to figure out what the heck it meant to start a company together.</p>

<p>Apart from our name and commitment to helping organizations that are making a positive impact in the world, it’s safe to say that pretty much everything else at ThinkShout has changed since that first day, including the grey in our beards! Personally, the challenges we face with constant change are among the things I like most about my job. As I often say, running ThinkShout has been a new job every 6 months or so, and I’m more excited than ever to see what the future will hold.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/fiveyears1-2.jpg" alt="fiveyears1-2jpg" /></p>

<p>In thinking about all that the team has accomplished and everything we’ve experienced these last five years, I spent some time looking at my first <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2012/01/lev/looking-back-2011/">annual wrap-up post</a>. What immediately stands out to me is that when we first started the company, most of our focus and pride came from talking about our technology contributions. We dreamt of being the “smartest geeks in the room” and bragged about how everyone at ThinkShout wrote code. Wow, was that ever naive and foolish. Just one of the many, MANY, lessons that Sean I learned as we stumbled down this path. We now understand that it takes so much more than solid technology to help an organization accomplish its goals. You need strategists to define solutions, designers to create delightful user experiences, and project managers to guide projects to success.</p>

<p>Of course, we are still inspired by open source innovations. In fact, this year the aggregate install base of our Drupal contributions peaked at 60,000 websites and we released perhaps our most innovative solution yet, <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen_raiser">RedHen Raiser</a>, a viral fundraising platform based on <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen">RedHen CRM</a>.</p>

<p>At the same time, our understanding of what it means to build a sustainable, values-driven business has matured. We have grown our team to 21 full-time staff, adding service offerings such as user experience design and digital fundraising strategy. We have also grown our leadership team, creating a “small council” of directors who’ve been tasked with making sure that we are responsive to the needs of both our staff and our customers.</p>

<p>It’s because of the strength of this team that we’ve also been able to work with some amazing clients this last year, including the relaunch of <a href="https://www.splcenter.org/">the Southern Poverty Law Center’s website</a>, and the kickoff of a new website for The Humane Society of America. We launched 11 client websites and helped 43 organizations craft compelling digital experiences for their constituents.</p>

<p>This last year saw us focus on more than just our client engagements, as we increased our investment into community engagement by almost 50%. We hosted and sponsored over a dozen local events, many focused on fostering diversity in the tech industry. Similarly, we sponsored six regional and five national conferences, with our team leading over 30 hours of community trainings at these events.</p>

<p>We also undertook a major initiative to <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/">redefine our mission, vision, and values</a>. Having these guideposts are critical so we don’t “lose our way” as we continue to grow.  And one of my proudest experiences of being part of this team, we achieved our long time goal of becoming B Corp certified. B Corp certification provides us with guidelines, metrics, and a community of practice for all of the business decisions that we make in support of our team, our clients, our local community, and the environment. B Corp certification is our a roadmap for continuing to make intentional choices that put people and the planet above profit as we grow and continue to change over the next five, ten, fifteen years and beyond.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/fiveyears2.jpg" alt="fiveyears2.jpg" /></p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2016 04:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/five-years/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/five-years/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Our Road to B Corp</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<h3 id="what-is-a-b-corp-time-for-homework">What is a B Corp? Time For Homework###</h3>

<p>Before ThinkShout, I’d never heard of a B Corp, but there it was, one of the  first projects I undertook upon my hire: “Get ThinkShout certified as a B Corp.”</p>

<p>Educating myself was step one. I watched the video “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V-VFZUFJwt4&amp;feature=youtu.be">B the Change</a>,” read the book “<a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/handbook">The B Corp Handbook</a>” by Ryan Honeyman, and combed the <a href="www.bcorporation.net">www.bcorporation.net</a> website to get a better and deeper understanding of what this movement was all about. I was blown away!</p>

<p>As stated on the site, “B Corps are certified by the nonprofit B Lab to meet rigorous standards of social and environmental performance, accountability, and transparency.” (We’ll get to the ‘rigorous’ part in a bit.) B Corp companies don’t want to be the best in the world - instead, they strive to be the best <em>for</em> the world. The change of that one word is transformative.</p>

<p>I realized how meaningful the B Corp movement is and how it would transform our company by making it a better place for our employees, a better steward of community and the environment. It’s the trifecta of awesome - there’s something for everyone and it’s all a force for positive change.</p>

<h3 id="getting-certified-capturing-the-data">Getting Certified: Capturing the Data###</h3>

<p>In order to become certified as a B Corp, there’s a rigorous ‘Assessment’ process. Think of it like the final exam in the toughest class you’ve ever taken but you <em>have</em> to pass it in order to land your dream job. On the Assessment, a score of 80 out of a potential perfect 200 is considered passing. Don’t be fooled into thinking, “Only 80?!” A lot goes into the scoring process, and data is pulled from multiple areas: Human Resources, Building Management, Purchasing, Financials, Employee Benefits . . . it’s all gathered, compiled and scored.</p>

<p>This assessment is <em>hard</em>. We’ve been in business for six years. During that time, we’ve experienced a significant amount of growth and change. Like many companies, we have policies, procedures, and values, but there wasn’t a consistent set of written procedures, or a practice of putting philosophies to paper. There was a general cultural ethos, but without it being written and <em>established</em>, we weren’t going to get points for it on the assessment.</p>

<p>The Assessment is organized into 6 parts: Governance, Workers, Community, Environment, Impact Business Models, and a Disclosure Questionnaire. I haven’t counted how many questions there are, but if you print it out, it’s 35 pages. A typical question, “What percent of full time workers have participated in external professional development opportunities or lifelong learning opportunities (paid in advance, reimbursed or subsidized by the company) in the past fiscal year?” 35 pages of questions like this and reaching a score of 80 on our first Assessment starts to feel like more of a substantial accomplishment.</p>

<p>Admittedly, it took the better part of a year to complete the Assessment, and if I had prepared better at the onset, that timeframe would have been much shorter and perhaps less stressful - although no less of an accomplishment!</p>

<h3 id="it-could-have-been-better">It Could Have Been Better###</h3>

<p>Because I was a new employee to ThinkShout, I wasn’t prepared to answer the kinds of questions required by the Assessment. By the time I put into place much of the infrastructure needed to complete the Assessment, I realized that the Assessment had already been started by my predecessor. Not knowing how she calculated some of the information was initially confusing, but it also encouraged me to dive deeper into the data. What ensued was about six months of reports, writing, and entering data into the Assessment until we were within range of the certification.</p>

<p>Now that we’re certified, I can look back and think about how I could have better prepared for this process. Take my advice:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Study the assessment before actually starting it. Read it so you know what data you’ll need to gather. Use it as the guiding blueprint or playbook.</li>
  <li>Read the book “<a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/handbook">The B Corp Handbook</a>” by Ryan Honeyman and take the guidance it offers.</li>
  <li>Make a plan. Identify the ‘pre-work’ that needs to be done. For example, if you have a mission statement <em>that is documented</em>, points are earned. If it exists but isn’t documented, no points.</li>
  <li>Identify key people. Who has the information you need? Who has the authority to make changes? Are there B Corp evangelists in the company, and are they available to help?
What does it mean to you, and to employees?</li>
</ul>

<p>Becoming a B Corp changed my relationship with ThinkShout. It gave everything I do a deeper meaning. Now, for example, when considering employee benefits, our B Corp status is part of the equation. Are we taking the welfare of our employees into consideration when we make changes? When we consider office space, we think about the location and its proximity to public transportation. We think about the energy and water usage. It reminds us of <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/">our own values</a>: when we engage with a potential new client, we think about their own mission and what change <em>they</em> are making in the world.</p>

<p>I’m proud that ThinkShout is a B Corp. When I’m talking with someone who is interested in working here, I can tell them about the B Corp certification and what it means. Almost immediately, we establish whether or not the B Corp message and mission aligns with their values.</p>

<p>Shortly after we certified and announced it to the office, a new employee shared that she’d never worked for a company that made their employees and the community such a high priority. Yeah. That is amazing.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/our-road-to-bcorp/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/our-road-to-bcorp/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Being the Change - Becoming a B Corp</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/thinkshout-bcorp-blog__2_.jpg" alt="thinkshout-bcorp.jpg" /></p>

<p>When <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2009/07/sean/why-thinkshout-why-now/">Sean</a> and <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/01/lev/levs-take-new-thinkshout-inc/">I founded</a> ThinkShout in January of 2011, one of the first things we did was sit down and write the following Mission Statement:</p>

<p><em>ThinkShout helps progressive organizations achieve their goals through web strategy and open source software. We treat our business and nonprofit clients as partners. Our motivation comes from knowing that they make the world a better place.</em></p>

<p>This Mission Statement worked well for the two of us. Our focus was 100% on our clients. We had a tiny environmental footprint, as we were just two guys with laptops and rented desks. We had no staff, so we didn’t yet need to think about organizational culture. Our considerations of the workplace environment didn’t go much further than choosing Spotify channels in our tiny office. The bottom line is that we loved using open source technology to help nonprofits have a positive impact and in our early days, our mission, as well as many other things, just <em>worked</em>.</p>

<p>In the ensuing years, we’ve been very fortunate and, well, haven’t made too much of a mess of things. We’ve connected with wonderful, forward-thinking <a href="http://thinkshout.com/work/">clients</a> who are, indeed, making the world a better place. We have a <a href="http://thinkshout.com/team/">team</a> of 21 talented, dedicated, and passionate individuals. And we’re still <a href="http://thinkshout.com/careers/">growing</a>. We have a clearly defined culture representing our values, and a gorgeous workplace to match. We laid a solid foundation for growth on top of a strong management team and cohesive organizational structure. Of course, apart from surrounding ourselves with great people, Sean and I are personally responsible for very little of all this.</p>

<h3 id="staying-focused-through-growth">Staying Focused Through Growth###</h3>

<p>As I often like to say, I have a completely new job every 6 months or so - which is a good thing. If Sean and I weren’t continually surprised, frustrated, and elated with the experience of building a company, we’d run the risk of losing our edge. New challenges are, after all, a prerequisite for new opportunities.</p>

<p>Growth brings many challenges:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Larger projects with higher stakes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A diverse team with varying work styles and needs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A more complex organizational structure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nuanced financial decisions with far reaching implications.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>To put it more succinctly, there’s just a lot more going on! Consequently, we realized that we needed to put together a better system to make sure that our growing leadership team and our overall business stays on track with our original values and goals.</p>

<p>So, we’ve made two strong investments this year. First, we embarked on a robust, 3-month strategic planning process culminating in a new missions, vision, and set of values. Second, we took the formal steps to become a “Beneficial Corporation” (or B Corp).</p>

<h3 id="our-new-vision-mission-and-values-statements">Our New Vision, Mission, and Values Statements###</h3>

<p><strong>Our Vision</strong> is to use technology and strategy to elevate organizations creating positive change in the world.</p>

<p><strong>Our Mission</strong> is to craft compelling open source engagement solutions in partnership with forward-thinking clients.</p>

<p>And our Corporate Values are the following:</p>

<p><strong>Innovation:</strong> We embrace flexibility and creativity in the approaches we take to serve our clients and staff. We recognize that our success is supported through refinement of our processes.</p>

<p><strong>Expertness:</strong> We bring proficiency and good judgement to problem solving, both internally and in serving clients. We are dedicated to being among the best at what we do, fostering a culture of continuous education and improvement.</p>

<p><strong>Respect:</strong> We respect our clients as experts in their field and honor their missions and resources. We respect the individuality and diversity of our peers. We treat each other with respect and kindness, honoring the different but equally important contributions that we all make in service to our mission.</p>

<p><strong>Helpfulness:</strong> We support the nonprofit and broader technology community through our open source contributions. We are committed to supporting our peers in their daily work and professional growth. We help organizations make the world a better place.</p>

<p><strong>Sustainability:</strong> We are committed to building a stable business that our team and clients can depend upon over time. Through our business practices, values, and client engagements, we seek to improve local communities and to have a more positive impact on the environment.</p>

<p>Circling back to our original Mission Statement at our founding, you’ll notice that at ThinkShout’s core, we hold the same values. However, our new Vision, Mission, and Values Statements provide us with a more complete framework. Specifically, they provide us with a roadmap for how we want to engage daily with our own team, our clients, and the larger world around us.</p>

<h3 id="becoming-a-certified-b-corp">Becoming a Certified B Corp###</h3>

<p>In addition to fleshing out our vision for the company, we worked hard this year to achieve <a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/community/thinkshout-inc">B Corp certification</a>. <a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/what-are-b-corps/the-non-profit-behind-b-corps">B Corp</a> represents both a framework and certification from the nonprofit B Lab, as well as a legal status in select states, with the goal of holding corporations accountable to society as well as shareholders.</p>

<p>First, we made adjustments to the company’s articles of incorporation to ensure that “benefits to society” can be prioritized over increasing shareholder wealth in making financial decisions for ThinkShout. Technically speaking, without this change, as executives of a corporation, we are legally required to prioritize shareholder value over commitment to community and the environment.</p>

<p>Second, and more importantly, B Corp certification provides us with guidelines, metrics, and a community of practice for all of the business decisions that we make in support of our team, our clients, our local community, and the environment. In other words, we now have a roadmap for continuing to make intentional choices that put people and the planet above profit.</p>

<p>Taken together, our refined mission, vision, and values, and B Corp certification give us a framework to ensure that ThinkShout stays true to its roots, and that it continues to grow. Onward and upward!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
