<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/thinkshout/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>The End of the Beginning</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p><img src="http://static.independent.co.uk/s3fs-public/thumbnails/image/2013/10/14/12/2638166.jpg" alt="Winston Churchill" /></p>

<p>While I fully realize it’s not fair to compare a major turning point at an organization to one in an existential battle over the future of the civilized world, Winston Churchill was clearly onto something. At this point, the news is out that <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/stepping-down-as-ceo-stepping-into-colorado/">Sean is leaving ThinkShout</a>. I still wince when I see those words, although we’re all getting used to the idea.</p>

<p>In my mind, the “beginning” in this case is the early stages of a company started by a couple of guys with a vague notion of wanting to <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/">do well by doing good</a>. At this point, ThinkShout is so much more. It is 22 intelligent, compassionate, talented, and dedicated professionals. It is a collection of accumulated knowledge and processes that allow us to partner with organizations like the <a href="https://www.splcenter.org/">Southern Poverty Law Center</a> that we look upon with awe and respect. It is the combined innovation of 60,000 websites running on our contributions. It is the experience and insights we can offer on how to best use those tools.</p>

<p>As we built this company, Sean and I were often challenged by mentors and our leadership team on what our goals were for ThinkShout. The answers varied over the years, but one key point was consistent: we both dreamed of building an organization that was much more than either of us, that could live on when we inevitably moved on.</p>

<p>For Sean, that time is now. And, even though he’s incredibly humble and won’t say it himself, he’s leaving with his head held high, incredibly proud of having accomplished what he set out to do.</p>

<p>I can’t thank him enough for going on this journey with me these past 6 years. I don’t want to sugarcoat things. There have been plenty of challenges, as there are in any relationship, but Sean’s been a wonderful business partner. He’s challenged me in countless ways, supported me when I’ve been down, and done the dirty work to make the business run when I’ve played the prima donna engineer role. In short, he’s set ThinkShout up for amazing success as he moves on. And for that, we’re all grateful.</p>

<p>Alright, so that’s the beginning. What’s next?</p>

<p>As part of Sean’s transition, we’ve made a number of promotions that were already under consideration that I’m incredibly proud to announce here.</p>

<h3 id="brett-meyer-chief-strategy-officer">Brett Meyer, Chief Strategy Officer</h3>

<p>Brett will run point on our business development efforts, as well as continue to lead our strategy and UX teams. He will work closely with Stephanie Gutowski, who was recently promoted to Marketing Manager. He will also support Natania LeClerc, who will lead ThinkShout’s new digital fundraising practice area. We’re also growing our strategy team, with an immediate opening for a <a href="http://thinkshout.com/careers/">Senior UX Designer</a> and more to come. Brett has been pivotal in getting ThinkShout to where it is today and his ascension to this leadership position is well deserved. He crafts our solutions in the sales process and during discovery, leads our UX and IA practice, and is a well-recognized thought leader in the nonprofit technology community. Just try getting a seat during one of his talks at the <a href="http://www.nten.org/ntc/">Nonprofit Technology Conference</a>.</p>

<h3 id="alex-macmillan-chief-operating-officer">Alex MacMillan, Chief Operating Officer</h3>

<p>In her role as Director of Project Management, Alex has led our PM team, defined our project delivery process, and managed resource allocation. In her 2 years with us, she has become the heartbeat of our projects, drastically increasing client satisfaction and project success rates. As COO, she’ll also take on oversight over the financial health of individual projects and the company as a whole. We’re also growing our project management team, looking for another <a href="http://thinkshout.com/careers/">senior project manager</a> to partner with our clients to help them have a positive impact.</p>

<p>With Alex’s new role, Krista Van Veen, who has been our Operations Manager, has a new title: Manager of Culture and People. This represents her focus on HR, recruiting, and community engagement, although she’ll continue to play a critical role in managing ThinkShout’s finances. Krista has worked hard to convert our vision and values into actual cultural changes, as demonstrated by her leadership in attaining our recent <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/our-road-to-bcorp">B Corp certification</a>.</p>

<h3 id="tauno-hogue-chief-technology-officer">Tauno Hogue, Chief Technology Officer</h3>

<p>Tauno is ThinkShout’s most senior employee, having been with us, quite literally, since the beginning. In that time, he’s grown from a talented developer into the leader of our engineering team. He takes on some of our most complex technical challenges, provides mentorship, and helps define our development workflow. In his new role as CTO, he’ll continuing doing more of the same, along with ensuring that we continue to offer innovative open source solutions for our forward-thinking clients. And, you guessed it, we’re also <a href="http://thinkshout.com/careers">hiring on the engineering side of things</a>.</p>

<p>Given that I had the title of CTO, clearly something else has to change. I am assuming Chief Executive Officer (CEO) responsibilities. This will entail setting the strategic direction of the company in partnership with the leadership team, along with being an external representative of ThinkShout. Most importantly to me, I will remain very actively involved in crafting innovative technical solutions for the challenges facing our clients. But, really, my biggest job will be to stay out of the way of the amazing leadership that we now have in place.</p>

<blockquote>
<p style="font-size:1.4em">"To improve is to change; to be perfect is to change often."</p>
- Winston Churchill
</blockquote>

<p>Sticking with the Churchill theme, it’s important to note that this is far from the end of the changes that we expect to see at ThinkShout in the coming months.</p>

<p>First, and I mean this sincerely, there is absolutely nothing that we are doing perfectly. Far from it. We’ll continue to iterate on everything, including our organizational structure. We’re going to get some stuff wrong, and we’ll adjust accordingly.</p>

<p>But, on the whole, I have never been more confident in, and excited for, the future. We’re due to kick off our largest project yet with an organization that we’ve all dreamed of working with. We have four Drupal 8 projects lined up to kick off in Q1. We’re launching a new Digital Fundraising practice area. We’re welcoming five new team members over the next few months.</p>

<p>None of this would be possible without everything that Sean has put into ThinkShout up to this point. For that, we thank him. And we wish him luck on his next grand adventure – which, rumor has it, might involve pickling or waxed canvas accessories… Stay tuned, I know it will be great.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/end-of-the-beginning/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/end-of-the-beginning/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Stepping Down As CEO, Stepping Into Colorado</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>As most of my friends and colleagues in the Drupal and nonprofit technology communities know, I joyously became a dad about a year and a half ago. Stepping into fatherhood involved a move to Denver, away from our Portland-based team at ThinkShout. Since then, I’ve flown over 100,000 miles, juggling my responsibilities as CEO at ThinkShout with those as a parent in Colorado. It’s been tricky to say the least. I am incredibly thankful for the support of my team, especially that of my thoughtful and always encouraging business partner, Lev Tsypin.</p>

<p>That said, it’s time for a change. It’s time for me to be fully present in Colorado, focused on my family, embracing this new community.</p>

<p>After a lot of conversation with Lev over the past few months, I have decided to step down as CEO at ThinkShout. I have handed over my ownership for an incremental buyout that keeps the company in a strong place financially.</p>

<p>I will continue to serve this team and our clients through this transition for the next three to six months as our Director of Sales. Then, I look forward to taking a break from the world of professional services and technology to try some new things. (Honest to goodness, professional pickling is on my short list. Let’s chat more about that over a beer.)</p>

<p>I will always be an advocate for this incredible team.</p>

<p>I am sad to leave right as we start tackling a new wave of technology challenges with the release of Drupal 8, as we begin to serve exciting new clients like the Humane Society, and as we kick off a new digital fundraising practice area.</p>

<p>At the same time, I could not feel more confident in the future of this company. We have invested heavily the last two years in our management team, organizational structure, and processes. We have attracted talented engineers, project managers, designers, and strategists. While hopefully some folks on staff will notice that I’m gone, as a team, ThinkShout will not miss a beat in serving its mission-driven clients.</p>

<p>ThinkShout will continue telling stories of good people making lasting change. Now I just get to tell ThinkShout’s story as fan and supporter in Colorado.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/ernie_sean.jpg" alt="ernie_sean.jpg" /></p>

<p><em>(My son Ernie is a big fan of ThinkShout, too.)</em></p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/stepping-down-as-ceo-stepping-into-colorado/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/stepping-down-as-ceo-stepping-into-colorado/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Five Years</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Five years ago today, Sean and I met on the rainy steps of our attorney’s office in downtown Portland. We walked inside and proceeded to sign a small mountain of paperwork to form ThinkShout, Incorporated. Then, the two of us biked back to the 100 square foot office we’d been sharing for the previous year to figure out what the heck it meant to start a company together.</p>

<p>Apart from our name and commitment to helping organizations that are making a positive impact in the world, it’s safe to say that pretty much everything else at ThinkShout has changed since that first day, including the grey in our beards! Personally, the challenges we face with constant change are among the things I like most about my job. As I often say, running ThinkShout has been a new job every 6 months or so, and I’m more excited than ever to see what the future will hold.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/fiveyears1-2.jpg" alt="fiveyears1-2jpg" /></p>

<p>In thinking about all that the team has accomplished and everything we’ve experienced these last five years, I spent some time looking at my first <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2012/01/lev/looking-back-2011/">annual wrap-up post</a>. What immediately stands out to me is that when we first started the company, most of our focus and pride came from talking about our technology contributions. We dreamt of being the “smartest geeks in the room” and bragged about how everyone at ThinkShout wrote code. Wow, was that ever naive and foolish. Just one of the many, MANY, lessons that Sean I learned as we stumbled down this path. We now understand that it takes so much more than solid technology to help an organization accomplish its goals. You need strategists to define solutions, designers to create delightful user experiences, and project managers to guide projects to success.</p>

<p>Of course, we are still inspired by open source innovations. In fact, this year the aggregate install base of our Drupal contributions peaked at 60,000 websites and we released perhaps our most innovative solution yet, <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen_raiser">RedHen Raiser</a>, a viral fundraising platform based on <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen">RedHen CRM</a>.</p>

<p>At the same time, our understanding of what it means to build a sustainable, values-driven business has matured. We have grown our team to 21 full-time staff, adding service offerings such as user experience design and digital fundraising strategy. We have also grown our leadership team, creating a “small council” of directors who’ve been tasked with making sure that we are responsive to the needs of both our staff and our customers.</p>

<p>It’s because of the strength of this team that we’ve also been able to work with some amazing clients this last year, including the relaunch of <a href="https://www.splcenter.org/">the Southern Poverty Law Center’s website</a>, and the kickoff of a new website for The Humane Society of America. We launched 11 client websites and helped 43 organizations craft compelling digital experiences for their constituents.</p>

<p>This last year saw us focus on more than just our client engagements, as we increased our investment into community engagement by almost 50%. We hosted and sponsored over a dozen local events, many focused on fostering diversity in the tech industry. Similarly, we sponsored six regional and five national conferences, with our team leading over 30 hours of community trainings at these events.</p>

<p>We also undertook a major initiative to <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/becoming-a-bcorp/">redefine our mission, vision, and values</a>. Having these guideposts are critical so we don’t “lose our way” as we continue to grow.  And one of my proudest experiences of being part of this team, we achieved our long time goal of becoming B Corp certified. B Corp certification provides us with guidelines, metrics, and a community of practice for all of the business decisions that we make in support of our team, our clients, our local community, and the environment. B Corp certification is our a roadmap for continuing to make intentional choices that put people and the planet above profit as we grow and continue to change over the next five, ten, fifteen years and beyond.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/fiveyears2.jpg" alt="fiveyears2.jpg" /></p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2016 04:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/five-years/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/01/five-years/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Looking Back on ThinkShout's first Year</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<div style="font-style:italic; float:left; margin: 0 10px 10px 0; width: 300px;"><img src="http://thinkshout.com/sites/default/files/images/inline/ts_team.jpg" style="width: 300px;" /><br />The ThinkShout team celebrates our one year anniversary</div>
<p>Almost exactly a year ago, after over a year of flirting with the idea of partnering, Sean and I finally tied the knot. Our initial goals when <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/01/lev/levs-take-new-thinkshout-inc">starting ThinkShout</a> were modest:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Bring on our first couple of team members.</li>
  <li>Expand our the base of amazing non-profits, social ventures, and progressive startups we work with while improving the service we provide to our existing clients.</li>
  <li>Expand our expertise in <a href="http://thinkshout.com/expertise#Web-based%20Mapping">mapping</a>, crm/asm, <a href="http://thinkshout.com/expertise#">discovery / strategy</a>, <a href="http://thinkshout.com/expertise#Technology%20Planning">technology planning</a>, <a href="http://thinkshout.com/expertise#Web%20Services%20and%20Integrations">web services / integrations</a>, and, of course, <a href="http://thinkshout.com/expertise#Drupal%20Development">Drupal development</a>.</li>
  <li>Participate and contribute to the Drupal community which we’re proud to be a part of.</li>
</ul>

<p>We certainly have a long ways to go, but we’re proud of how far we’ve come and are even more excited for what the year ahead holds.</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Launching exciting projects with <a href="http://dehen1920.com">Dehen 1920</a>, <a href="http://thinkshout.com/portfolio/world-wildlife-fund-fisheries-database">World Wildlife Fund</a>, <a href="http://manhattankayak.com/">Manhattan Kayak Company</a>, <a href="http://bacteria.bluewaterbaltimore.org/">Blue Water Baltimore</a>, and <a href="http://thinkshout.com/portfolio">many more</a>.</li>
  <li>Releasing several open source tools to help progressive organizations, including several new <a href="http://drupal.org/project/mailchimp">MailChimp releases</a>, a few <a href="http://drupal.org/project/modules?filters=tid%3A65%20drupal_core%3A103%20bs_project_sandbox%3A0&amp;solrsort=sis_project_release_usage%20desc&amp;text=openlayers">OpenLayers modules</a> and the first <a href="http://drupal.org/project/leaflet">Drupal Leaflet</a> integration to help tell stories with maps, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/wireframe_me">Wireframe ME</a> for rapid prototyping, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/vs_webform">VoteSmart webform</a> to promote advocacy, and <a href="http://drupal.org/project/registration">Entity Registrations</a>, a new platform for managing registrations with Drupal which we <a href="http://usecod.com/news/2012/cod-2012-update-new-co-maintainer-drupal-7-acquia">hope will be adopted</a> by <a href="http://drupal.org/project/cod">COD</a>.</li>
  <li>Kicking off new engagements with The <a href="http://www.givingforum.org/">Forum of Regional Associations of Grantmakers</a>, <a href="http://living-future.org/">International Living Future Institute</a>, <a href="http://www.lcrep.org/">Lower Columbia River Estuary Partnership</a>, <a href="http://openplans.org">OpenPlans</a>, <a href="http://theintertwine.org/">Metro / Intertwine</a>, <a href="http://willametteriverinitiative.org/">Willamette River Initiative</a>, <a href="http://www.scenichudson.org/">Scenic Hudson</a>, and American Public Media’s market place to name a few.</li>
  <li>Continuing our <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/06/lev/mailchimp-20-anatomy-drupal-module-rewrite">innovative partnership</a> with <a href="http://mailchimp.com">MailChimp</a>.</li>
  <li>Forming strategic partnerships with Acquia and Pantheon.</li>
  <li>Pushing the boundaries in the Drupal mapping space with our collection of map related modules and projects.</li>
  <li>Breaking ground on a native CRM/ASM initiative, <a href="http://redhencrm.com">RedHen</a>, which we plan on making significant progress on during Q1 of 2012.</li>
  <li>Attending DrupalCon Chicago and <a href="http://2011.badcamp.net/">BADCamp</a> in Berkley, where we presented on pooling resources towards a common goal at the non-profit summit.</li>
  <li>Adding Andrea, Brandon, and Tauno to the <a href="http://thinkshout.com/team">ThinkShout team</a>. Seriously, they’re all amazing and we couldn’t have made it this far without each of them. The year ahead holds so much process as we refine our processes and really come together as a team.</li>
  <li>Moving into our new office in the <a href="http://www.ecotrust.org/">EcoTrust</a> building and being part of that dedicated and passionate community.</li>
  <li>Launching our sexy new <a href="http://thinkshout.com">responsive website</a>. Great job to everyone involved, especially Andrea who designed it and developed the theme.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="looking-ahead-to-2012">Looking ahead to 2012</h2>

<p>I’ll avoid a list so that it can’t be held over my head :) That said, we’re excited to release a native Drupal association management platform, come together as a team to do amazing work, work on exciting new projects while continuing to server our existing clients, add a new developer to the team, contribute more to the Drupal community we’re so proud to be a part of, and, most importantly, have a blast while making the world just a smidgen better, one Drupal site at a time.</p>

<p>Hope the new year is filled with promise for everyone. Thanks, the ThinkShout team.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2012/01/lev/looking-back-2011/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2012/01/lev/looking-back-2011/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>What we're up to; what we're into</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Alas, the “we should blog about that” queue is getting pretty heavy here at the office. It’s been a busy ten months since Lev and I officially opened the doors here at ThinkShout, Inc. And as we’ve been talking with developers this month about coming on board with the team, we’ve realized that we’re missing an opportunity to share with the community what’s been inspiring us in our own work, as well as in the Drupal community at large.</p>

<p>This blog post does a poor job of addressing that fact. But here goes…</p>

<h2 id="what-were-into">What we’re into…</h2>

<h3 id="responsive-design">Responsive design</h3>

<p>Over the last two months we’ve come to embrace responsive design as the starting point on every project for which we can influence site architecture decisions. Diving into responsive has affected almost every aspect of our sales, development and project management processes. It’s changed the way that we scope projects, the way that we prioritize features, the way that choose graphic design partners, and the way that we choose browser-based technologies for building interactive maps, jquery-driven slideshows, etc.</p>

<p>Interestingly, in embracing responsive we’re also managing to get ourselves out of the IE6/7/8 cross-browser support business. By <em>selling</em> responsive design in the project estimation process, we are better able to convince clients of the value in embracing modern browser platforms - as opposed to developing for the lowest of the low compatibility issues.</p>

<p>Soon we’ll have a couple case studies and technical write-ups of our responsive theming work - as well as how responsive has affected our wireframing process. But what I can say now is that we’re designing for mobile <em>first</em> and that we’re deep into the <a href="http://drupal.org/project/omega">Omega</a> theme camp.</p>

<h3 id="leaflet-and-mapbox">Leaflet and MapBox</h3>

<p>As maintainers of several <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/09/lev/openlayers-love-drupal-7">OpenLayers-based modules</a>, we’ve been involved in the Drupal mapping space for quite some time. However, because of our interest in mobile and HTML5, this summer we started work on a new <a href="http://drupal.org/project/leaflet">Leaflet module</a> for Drupal. We’ve also been getting heavily into Development Seed’s <a href="http://mapbox.com">MapBox</a> tool suite. We’ve been doing our own custom cartography work, producing watershed-based map <a href="http://tiles.mapbox.com/thinkshout/map/map-1318268325327">tilesets</a>. In addition, this winter we will be helping Oregon’s <a href="http://theintertwine.org/">The Intertwine</a> launch a new urban trails guide for the Portland area which leverages responsive design, Leaflet, and custom Tilemill tiles served up via Tilestream.</p>

<h2 id="what-were-up-to">What we’re up to…</h2>

<p>The truth is that there’s not much difference between what we are <em>into</em> and what we’re <em>up to</em>. We are really fortunate to work with clients to share our interest in open source contributions and who give us the opportunity to tinker with new technologies. But for the purposes of this post, I guess I’ll make the distinction.</p>

<h3 id="content-migrations">Content Migrations</h3>

<p>Geeky, I know…But our newest team member, <a href="http://thinkshout.com/team#brandon">Brandon Lee</a>, has been enjoying the heck out of working on a complex migration of the content from two Drupal 6.x sites and one Drupal 5.x site to a single Drupal 7.x site. In the process, he’s had the opportunity to roll up his sleeves and get into the weeds of the <a href="http://drupal.org/project/migrate">Migrate 2.x</a> module.</p>

<p>Lev and I couldn’t be more excited for Brandon to develop this passion. I’m doubtful that we’d ever try to position ourselves as the next <a href="http://cyrve.com/">Cyrve</a>, but it’s great to bring on this skill set.</p>

<h3 id="event-registrations">Event Registrations</h3>

<p>This spring we had the opportunity to develop a custom event management tool for our friends at <a href="http://thinkshout.com/portfolio/manhattan-kayak-company">Manhattan Kayak Company</a> in NYC. Abstracting that work into a Drupal contributed module, we’ve been actively working on an entity-base event sign-up tool for Drupal 7.x. The project is currently called <a href="http://drupal.org/project/registration">Entity Registrations</a>. We’re talking with the good folks who manage the <a href="http://drupal.org/project/signup">Signup module</a> about porting our work there as the 7.x-2.x branch of sign-up, as well as potentially working the module into Drupal’s <a href="http://drupal.org/project/cod">Conference Organizing Distribution, cod</a>.</p>

<p>We’re also excited to have a number of larger client engagements this winter that will fund new features for this entity-based registration system, an approach we’ve had some success with and discussed at the recent <a href="http://2011.badcamp.net/drupal-non-profit-summit">BADCamp NP Summit</a>. We anticipate releasing CRM integration, paid event management, and group-based sign-up features over the next few months - so stay tuned.</p>

<h3 id="mailchimp-mailchimp-mailchimp">MailChimp, MailChimp, MailChimp</h3>

<p>MailChimp is one of our favorite technologies - as well as one of our favorite clients. Over the last 10 months, the usage of our <a href="http://drupal.org/project/mailchimp">MailChimp integration module</a> has more than doubled to just shy of 6K. This summer we released an integration with MailChimp’s transactional email service - allowing Drupal sites to send all outgoing mail via MailChimp, as well as to collect robust delivery analytics from the service.</p>

<p>With a number of CRM-related projects on our horizon, we will be working hard over the next few months to build out a third integration with MailChimp’s campaign feature - which, in short, will allow us to develop bulk-email tools natively in Drupal.</p>

<h3 id="native-drupal-crm">Native Drupal CRM</h3>

<p>In addition to a number of Salesforce integration projects, this winter we will be lighting a fire under <a href="http://redhencrm.com">Red Hen CRM</a> - the native Drupal 7.x CRM initiative we started just prior to DrupalCon Chicago. It’s still unclear whether or not we’ll piggy back this work off of another project, such as Trellon’s CRM initiative. Regardless of the details, we are very excited for the opportunity to contribute more time, energy, and code to this important Drupal initiative.</p>

<h2 id="other-teasers">Other teasers…</h2>

<p>Obviously there’s always more to get excited about. So, here are a few phrases describing other stuff that we’re excited for tackling this winter: open data, custom JSON parsers for the Feeds module, the Open App Marketplace, Drupal 7.x distributions, <a href="http://getpantheon.com">Pantheon</a>, custom Solr facets, the Media module, QR codes, smarter usage of EntityFieldQuery, developing our own Drupal-base virtual project board, etc…</p>

<h2 id="help-us">Help us…</h2>

<p>That’s right. We’ve got a lot going on and are looking to bring on another senior-level Drupal engineer. So, if you know anybody who would like to live in always-sunny PDX, Oregon - have them check out the following <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/10/sean/thinkshout-hiring">announcement</a>.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/11/sean/catching-up/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/11/sean/catching-up/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Lev's Take on the New ThinkShout, Inc.</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.levelos.com/files/thinkshout_logo.png" alt="thinkshout-logo" height="200" width="300" style="float:right; margin: 0 0 10px 10px;" />When I started Level Online Strategy back in 2004, I never intended to remain on my own as long as I have. I assumed that I’d soon find a partner who shared my vision about how to run a consulting company and my passion for helping progressive organizations through our work. In large part because I was too busy running the business, I never found that person, until I met <a href="http://twitter.com/sean_larkin">Sean Larkin</a> back in the summer of 2009. He was just starting out on his own, dba ThinkShout. We realized early on that we had complimentary skills, similar approaches to business, and wanted to serve the same base of clients, in our case nonprofits and social ventures having a positive impact in their communities. Neither one of us was quite willing to give up our independence and personal brands, at least yet, but we did start collaborating and had some huge wins, including <a href="http://saveourgulf.org">SaveOurGulf</a>, <a href="http://maps.lcrep.org">The Lower Columbia River Estuary Partnership</a>, <a href="http://geomeridian.com">GeoMeridian</a>, and our work together on <a href="http://drupal.org/project/watershednow">Watershed Now</a>. During that time, we also released several modules back to the community (<a href="http://drupal.org/project/mapstraction">Mapstraction</a>, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/qr_codes">QR Codes</a>, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/openlayers_taxonomy">Openlayers Taxonomy</a>, and <a href="http://drupal.org/project/openlayers_kml_layer">Openlayers KML Layer</a>, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/vs_webform">VoteSmart Webform</a>, <a href="http://drupal.org/project/watershednow">Watershed Now</a>), something we found much easier and more rewarding working in tandem.</p>

<p>Which brings us to the present day. After our successful year and half long trial, we’re finally pulling the trigger and <em>tying the knot</em>, so to speak. As of January, 2011, Sean and I are equal partners in <a href="http://thinkshout.com">ThinkShout, Inc.</a>, a new Oregon corporation. The process hasn’t always been easy, but it has been extremely rewarding. We have a full slate of exciting projects for Q1 and beyond, as well as some top secret product initiatives that we can’t wait to share with the world. As a partnership with room to grow we can <strong>much</strong> better serve our existing clients, provide a broader and deeper set of services and products, and give much more back to the community. And by community I mean the places we live, work, and play, organizations we work with, and, of course, the <a href="http://drupal.org">Drupal</a> community itself within which we operate. To celebrate, we’ve given <a href="http://thinkshout.com">ThinkShout.com</a> a new look and feel, including a new logo. Well, that’s at least the start of the celebration.</p>

<p>I am 100% committed to my existing Level OS clients, to whom I owe so much from the last 6 years. I will continue serving them however it suits them best, be it through Level OS or ThinkShout. For the most part, I plan on transitioning all of my consulting work to ThinkShout (After all, having 2 throats to choke is better than one!), and keep Level OS around for the occasional side venture, a personal outlet on the web, and for any work that may not fit within ThinkShout. I’ll do most of my work related blogging over on ThinkShout.com, and hopefully will have time for more of it now. I’ll still post the occasional web/geek/personal interest story here on levelos.com.</p>

<p>Oh, and we’re also moving to a new office in February, over in the <a href="http://www.ecotrust.org/">Ecotrust</a> building, which we’re thrilled about. <a href="http://nedspace.com">NedSpace</a> has been an amazing and nurturing environment, and I couldn’t recommend it more, but it’s time for us to move on. So that’s the big news. Please chime in with any thoughts or questions. It’s a big move for us, but, again, we couldn’t be more excited about the future.</p>

<p><em>This post was originally published on levelos.com at http://www.levelos.com/blog/2011/01/thinkshout-inc.</em></p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2011 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/01/lev/levs-take-new-thinkshout-inc/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2011/01/lev/levs-take-new-thinkshout-inc/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
