<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/drupal-community/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>A Tale of Two Devsigners</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>It’s June, which means <a href="http://www.devsignercon.com/">Devsigner</a> is just around the corner so, naturally, we’ve got design on the brain. What’s Devsigner? Well, I’m glad you asked. Devsigner is a conference held here in the Pacific Northwest geared towards front end developers and development-minded designers. Sessions focus on the relationship between design and web development, bridging the gap that separates the design from the code. The math looks like this: developer + designer = devsigner.</p>

<p>ThinkShout’s own devsigners <a href="http://thinkshout.com/team/josh/">Josh Riggs</a> (User Experience Lead) and <a href="http://thinkshout.com/team/eric/">Eric Paxton</a> (Front End Engineer), will be speaking at this conference at the end of the month. I sat down with Josh and Eric to learn a little bit more about their design process, and how we work with our nonprofit clients to ensure that their sites don’t just work, but that they also deliver a fantastic user experience.</p>

<p><strong><em>You two make up the dynamic design duo here at ThinkShout. What do your respective roles entail? How do you leverage your different skill sets?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Josh</strong>: My role as the UX lead right now is handling all aspects of user experience and visual design. I’m responsible for interpreting site maps and requirements, plus things like client/user needs and creating a user interface out of that. That starts with wireframing and ends with a visual design layer.</p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: My role as Front End Engineer is very much in the implementation phase. Though I do advise in the discovery and budgeting phase, just so we can be sure that we can actually implement what the client wants. It’s nice because in the past, before joining the ThinkShout team, I’d done the whole gamut. From the requirements gathering phase to wireframing, and then the implementation. Here at ThinkShout, I’ve found my sweet spot. I do occasional wireframing, but I get to focus on lots of implementation. I also implement Josh’s designs. I write a lot of Javascript and <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/07/getting-started-with-sass-for-drupal-and-zen-part-ii/">Sass</a>, basically.</p>

<p><strong>Josh</strong>: Eric is like the alchemist. He takes the metals - the designs from me - and turns them into websites. There is actually a large spectrum in between where my responsibilities stop and Eric’s begin. We still talk about things like, how do we go from an idea being on a screen, to that idea being a functioning website? We’re constantly thinking about how to best utilize our respective skillsets, always reevaluating our process to improve upon it.</p>

<p><strong><em>What’s a recent project that you’ve really enjoyed working on?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: <a href="http://selma.splcenter.org/">The SPLC (Southern Poverty Law Center) microsite</a>. I thought that was very well done. Josh did a lot of the front end work on that and I came in and did the site optimization, which is what I’ll be talking about at Devsigner. I thought that went really smoothly because at that time, all the work he’d done in the browser went directly to implementation. We were able to take exactly what he’d designed and <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/03/media-optimization-with-splc/">just build off of </a><a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/03/media-optimization-with-splc/">it</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/devsigner_0.png" alt="devsigner_0" /></p>

<p><strong><em>Can you talk a little bit about what the design process for the SPLC microsite was like, Josh?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Josh</strong>: We happened to be working on that right around the same time as I was doing wireframes for the upcoming <a href="http://www.splcenter.org/">SPLC</a> main site that we’re redesigning. We were already doing a lot of thinking about their content and what their needs were. Because the <a href="http://thinkshout.com/work/splc/selma/">Selma: Bridge to the Ballot</a> movie was coming out on the anniversary of the Selma March, we wanted to have this ready to go in time for that day. There was no way we were going to launch the whole SPLC site along with it - we were too early in development for that - so we decided to split that project up and give them a campaign microsite that would be easy to build while we continued to work on their main site.</p>

<p>A lot of that meant working with their team to define their content needs. I began with basic wireframes in <a href="http://bohemiancoding.com/sketch/">Sketch</a>, and uploaded them into <a href="http://www.invisionapp.com">Invision</a> to give them interactivity. As SPLC came up with more fidelity to what their needs were, we solidified the visual designs. Luckily, they already had a lot of assets that their really great internal design team had created for the movie, so I was able to go off of that style. I took their visual style and applied it to the wireframes and at that point, I went to Eric for a consultation and said, “Ok, if we’re going to build this in <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/10/success-building-cmsless-production-sites-with-jekyll/">Jekyll</a>, what’s the best way to do this as far as the architecture goes?” Eric was a huge help in regards to file structure. He wrote a great rake script to automate all the Jekyll, Sass, and Javascript components. That’s when I jumped in and rebuilt what I’d done in Sketch, and added more fidelity with HTML and Sass. I then passed it onto to Eric so he could do his unicorn magic.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/devsigner_1.png" alt="devsigner_1" /></p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: And that’s a nice part about where our skills overlap: we can get closer to what we want. He’s a better designer than I am. My strengths lie in the code. I’ve designed when I had to, but it’s not my forte, so it’s nice to have Josh’s expertise. So these skill sets compliment each other. I feel comfortable handing over my implementation to design and saying, “Hey, can you polish the nav? Or the design?” Things like that.</p>

<p><strong><em>What design trends do you want to see more of? Or less of?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: I think <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flat_design">flat design</a> is getting boring. I’m starting to see a little bit more texture in the things we’ve done. Like patterns, not just flat design for the sake of flat design. There’s texture strategically used to make things look better. For instance, in the <a href="https://www.austinfoodbank.org/">Capital Area Food Bank of Texas</a> site, there’s a bit of a pattern in the footer. It’s not just a flat blue background with text. I really like patterns that are used to call out different sections of a design. It adds to it and brings something out of the page. It used to just be that admin interfaces were this flat. But now everything reflects that. Lots of rectangles. I personally like shapes and textures and patterns.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/devsigner_2.png" alt="devsigner_2" /></p>

<p><strong>Josh</strong>:  It’s tricky to know when to add life to what’s a very flat trend right now. I come from the old school world of web design, which was about how cool can you make your shadows look in Photoshop, how three-dimensional can you make things appear. Now that’s kind of like wearing skinny jeans in the late nineties, when you wouldn’t be caught dead wearing them. Or neon colors. So I think what’s happening is that it’s not <em>just</em> that flat design is popular. If you look at other design mediums, like automotive or architecture, there’s a phase with extreme ornate elements. You know, crazy fins, details, lights, every car had a custom badge. All that stuff. And then you have the modern era after that where everything gets streamlined and simplified. It’s more about the function over the form, and the function drives the form. You see the opposite in the Victorian era. Go walk along the St. Johns bridge and look up at a lamp. You’ll see these ornate, twisted little embellishments along the lamps. But the purpose of a lamp is to provide light. Those embellishments do nothing to support the function. They’re just there to make it look pretty.</p>

<p>I think we’re seeing a lot of that in digital design as it matures. We’re getting rid of the stuff that doesn’t support the function and focusing more on the <em>intent</em> of the users. While we’re taking that ornate-ness out of it, we’re also adding a lot more micro-interactions and animations. Things that actually help you do what you’re there to do. At first, I was kind of against that. But now that I think about it as post-modern design for the web, it makes more sense to me.</p>

<p><strong><em>How do you advise nonprofits on this? Do these same trends benefit nonprofits as much as they do for-profits?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: I think knowing your end user is what determines your path. A lot of nonprofits have similar goals as for-profits when it comes to their websites - they’re trying to tell a story and engage their users. But the main thing is, do the organizational goals reflect what the user is coming there for? For instance, we work with the <a href="http://thinkshout.com/work/la-conservancy/">LA Conservancy</a>. They work to preserve historical buildings in LA. We didn’t just look at them, and then try to make their website look like a pretty building. But we also had this discussion in LA about form versus function. But I wonder, where does that meet in the middle? That’s what I struggle with. Because I do think there’s value in ornate elements like that. They set a mood. So I think that’s part of function - that ornateness sets the mood you want to present to your users to help them feel the connection to the organization’s cause.</p>

<p><strong>Josh</strong>: Nearly every major design phase, whether it be automotive, architecture, art, whatever, there’s always a backlash to those current trends. So there will be backlash to flat web design. It may be a subculture, it may take over. But whenever something gets to be ubiquitous, there’s always someone who wants to do something totally different. It’ll be interesting to see what that is.</p>

<p><strong><em>I feel like that’s the nature of creativity… We see something, we make it part of our process, plus a spark of something new.</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: We all have things we’re influenced by. To me, Google stands out. They’ve really led in the trends that people are using. There’s a level of depth to their designs that make me feel like I can reach out and grab it. It’s flat in some ways, but yeah, there’s definitely some depth.</p>

<p><strong>Josh</strong>: Yeah, I think Google’s done a really great job. And you can see this happening in the app world. The current trend is also getting ubiquitous.</p>

<p><strong><em>Devsigner is at the end of the month and you both are leading your own sessions. Can you tell us a bit about them?</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Eric</strong>: My session is called “Optimization is User Experience.” I think this is something everybody can use, which is why it’s listed as a beginner talk. We learn web design, we learn app design, we release these things to the world where we don’t have control over devices and users’ bandwidth, so it’s important to know that this beautiful thing you’ve created can be experienced correctly regardless of what device it’s viewed on.</p>

<p><strong>Josh:</strong> So my session is based on something I’ve noticed. I worked on a lot of projects where there’s limited time, budget, or resources. Maybe there isn’t any resource for stock photography, or there’s just a really small team working on it. I’ve always had to find ways to be creative with what I have and with a small budget. I signed up to speak at <a href="http://rfrshpdx.org/">Refresh Portland</a> and I figured this might be a shared struggle and that other people could learn from my experience: how to stay under budget and still come up with a great, workable design. It’s called “Ballin’ on a Budget.”</p>

<p><em>Want to dig deeper into design with Josh and Eric and pick their brains? Come to <a href="http://www.devsignercon.com/">Devsigner</a>, which takes place during June 27-28 at the Pacific Northwest College of Art in Portland, Oregon. Check out the full session schedule on the Devsigner site. You can also follow Josh and Eric on Twitter at @joshriggs and @epxtn.</em></p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 11:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/06/tale-of-two-devsigners/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/06/tale-of-two-devsigners/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>DrupalCon LA - A Designer's Perspective</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Oh, man. After coming back from DrupalCon Los Angeles with my team at ThinkShout, my brain still hurts… but in a good way. You know, in that same way you feel after binge watching Dr. Who on Netflix leading up to the season finale where The Doctor and Clara… oops. No spoilers. Point being: it’s a feeling of intense brain explosion followed by inspiration and motivation to get up and kick some ass.</p>

<p>Besides attending some fantastic design and UX sessions, I also presented my own session about <a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/ballin-budget-how-create-great-design-without-breaking-bank">designing on a budget</a> and led a BoF about design and prototyping in Drupal. I made a lot of <a href="https://twitter.com/feliarex">awesome</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/jessemutz">new</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/ACFind">friends</a> and reconnected with <a href="https://twitter.com/deviantintegral">some</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/blakehall">old</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/makangus">ones</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kevishie">as</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/jponch">well</a>.</p>

<p>All in all, it was a great conference and LA was a fantastic host city. My team from ThinkShout and I covered a lot of ground - we found some great bars and restaurants, including my favorite stop, Grand Central Market (where I had an amazing <a href="https://twitter.com/joshriggs/status/598967276163829761">octopus tostada</a> from La Tostaderia).</p>

<p>But anyway, you’re not here to read about bars and restaurants in LA. Let’s talk Design at DrupalCon.</p>

<p>One thing that’s really impressed me about DrupalCon is just how much the breadth of UX and Design content has expanded over the last few years. This was my fourth DrupalCon: my first was 2011 in Chicago, followed by ‘13 in Portland and ‘14 in Austin. I was excited to see there were several sessions in the UX and Design track this year that were less technical, and more about design thinking and problem solving. Personally, I enjoy these kind of talks because I tend to walk away with some new insights into my own process. <strong><em>Design is not the same thing as Front End Development, and DrupalCon is finally realizing and embracing this.</em></strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/design_notes.jpg" alt="design_notes.jpg" /></p>

<h2 id="common-design-themes-from-drupalcon-la">Common Design Themes from DrupalCon LA</h2>

<p>Attending DrupalCon is a great way to get your finger on the pulse of what’s happening in the Drupal community. I’ve noticed a lot of changing trends in the years since my first DrupalCon, starting with the prevalence of responsive design. In the first DrupalCon session I gave in Portland in 2013, only about half the room raised their hands when I asked how many had worked on a responsive Drupal site. This year, nearly everyone raised their hand when I asked the same question. <strong><em>At this point, responsive design is implicit when designing a new Drupal site.</em></strong></p>

<p>Here are some other design and UX trends from this year’s DrupalCon:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>People are applying design thinking about much more than how a website looks.</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/meganerinmiller">Megan Erin Miller</a>, a designer at Stanford University, gave a fantastic talk about using Service Design to design <a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/designing-end-end-experiences-why-we-need-service-experience-design">end-to-end experiences</a>. According to Erin, “designing a website is not just about designing good user experience. It’s about designing new processes, new identities, and new partnerships.” I couldn’t agree more. Erin compared the process of building a website to designing a theme park. When you go to a theme park, your experience isn’t just about what happens when you ride the roller coaster. A good theme park experience starts when you see an ad on TV or get an email offer and book your trip online or over the phone. When you get to the theme park, your whole experience is planned and designed, from the moment you walk in the gate, to when you queue up in line for the roller coaster, and on to dining and buying souvenirs. As designers, we should be thinking of our websites as products and how our users interact with these products from all possible channels, and not just what browser they’re using on what device. I’m always looking for new perspectives for my personal design process, and I hope to use some service design techniques in my client work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Components, components, and more components!</strong> Just as the topic of “responsive design” dominated DrupalCon’s design sessions in years past, this year’s hot topic was component-based design. As websites and web apps get more complex and responsive, design needs to be streamlined and simplified. One way we can do that is to design modularly. Gone are the days of creating unique layouts for every page on a website (phew!). Instead, we need to be creating design systems that can be applied efficiently across the entire responsive website. Two great component-based design sessions from DrupalCon LA were, “<a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/new-design-workflow">The New Design Workflow</a>,” and “<a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/pattern-lab-collaboration-using-modular-design-principles">To The Pattern Lab!</a>” In addition to these sessions, I also attended a very informative BoF about CSS Style Guides lead by the one and only <a href="https://twitter.com/JohnAlbin">John Albin Wilkins</a>. At ThinkShout, we already take a component-based approach to design, but I certainly learned some great new ideas and techniques!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Longform Storytelling is the new black.</strong> As Drupal shifts its focus towards publishing and news, content creators are embracing <a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/styles-storytelling-cultivating-compelling-long-form-content">rich longform articles and stories</a>. According to <a href="https://twitter.com/Bjoran_Identity">Kristina Bjoran</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/circlish">Courtney Clark</a> of Forum One, “People generally learn more and remember more when more of their senses are engaged by a story. Stories that include images get about twice the engagement as text-only stories. Stories told with visual elements are instantly captivating. The more senses that are engaged, the more emotions will be engaged and the more memorable the experience will be.” We are including longform content features in many of our new client’s websites at ThinkShout, and it was really great to hear how other industry leaders do it successfully as well.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="design-drupal-and-the-future">Design, Drupal, and the Future</h2>

<p>Each year, the Drupal Association puts more thought into diversifying the session lineup, and it shows. There was a very conscious effort to get more design and UX content, as well as speakers from diverse experiences and backgrounds. To that, I say “Huzzah!” As someone who’s been designing Drupal sites for many years now, it’s great to see the design process being treated as more than just “making it look pretty.” Design and UX is now a core component of DrupalCon, and I’m proud to have helped along the way.</p>

<p>After a week of learning and sharing new ideas, meeting amazing people, and eating some darn good Mexican food, my brain is full and my heart is heavy. I can’t wait to see you all next year!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/a-designers-perspective/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/a-designers-perspective/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Committing to D8 Core - A Little Bit Goes a Long Way</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>It was the last day of DrupalCon LA and after a long week of sessions, getting to know fellow Drupalistas, and partying until the wee hours, I mustered what little brainpower I had left and made my way to the “First Timer’s Sprint.” Joined by my ThinkShout colleagues, Joe and Nancy, we arrived with beautiful visions of giving back to our community by contributing in some capacity to Drupal 8 core. And so it begins…</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/image_1.jpg" alt="image_1.jpg" /></p>

<p>We arrived just in time to set our development environment up with a couple hundred other hopeful contributors, and were pleasantly surprised by how quickly that process went and how helpful the mentors were. As soon as we were all set up, the conference staff sent us on our merry way into the next room.</p>

<p>As you may or may not know, Drupal core is enormous! It can be a big, daunting pile of directories and folders that can go down several levels. For a newer developer (and even more seasoned ones, I hear) it takes a great deal of time to navigate this powerful platform. As a result, I was faced with too many possible issues to work on and very little background for how the contributing process works. I’m willing to bet most engineers have been in a similar situation at one time or another and can likely relate. This experience has a name - it’s called “decision fatigue,” where one is faced with so many possibilities to choose from that they become overwhelmed and may even check out entirely. I was there.</p>

<p>Having recognized this feeling before, I piped up and explained to our mentor that we would work more effectively if we were given a single focus or direction. This seemed to work well, and he provided us with a handful of suggestions. That was all fine and good, but after looking at the “Novice” queue, I felt my deer-in-headlights gaze only worsen. Still hungry for a way to gain some practical experience, I reflected back on the options our mentor suggested. He mentioned that “rerolls are easy,” and that seemed like a good place for me to start.</p>

<p>Seizing the moment, I nabbed the nearest mentor and asked him if he could spare a few minutes to help walk me through a reroll. Fortunately, he had a moment to spare, and pointed me to the documentation. Interestingly, this mentor happened to identify with me as a site-builder with little coding experience, yet he was knowledgeable and knew enough Git tricks to be an active participant in the Drupal issue queues.</p>

<p>With this mentor by my side, we dove into the oldest D8 “needs reroll” issue and went to town. Much to my surprise, this issue didn’t take long, but it also helped that another contributor had already rerolled the patch. No problem! I made a comment stating that the patch had been rerolled, how old the issue was (seven years, in this case), and removed the “needs reroll” tag from the issue. Though it felt like a negligible change, my mentor reassured me that I’d  spared another developer from having to go through the same process and reach the same conclusion. Consequently, the issue had moved on to a more progressive state, and there was much rejoicing.</p>

<p>After that was said and done, I went back to the issue queue feeling a tad more confident. Just moments later, our original mentor rushed excitedly back to our table. “Who wants to commit to core?” he asked. We all looked around at each other, not quite sure what to make of it, and responded with a cautiously optimistic “sure, we can help!”</p>

<p>Everything happened rather quickly, which was surprising considering how long it takes to get an average issue through the complete process. Here’s how it went down: There was an issue. A dev in another sprinting room was asked to write a patch. Another dev revised the patch by improving it slightly, and it was then passed to our table to go through the review process. A dev evaluation was put forth, then the issue was passed back for additional review. Finally, it was submitted to be pushed into core.</p>

<p>This was my first DrupalCon and, little did I know, they have a very important tradition - every DrupalCon sprint ends with a live commit by Dries, the founder of Drupal. Our team was lucky enough to be part of this ritual! So, after a full week of delightful Drupal-related shenanigans, I found myself on stage pressing the enter key on Dries’ computer to push our commit to D8 core. The button was pushed and the explosion of celebration and cheers from the audience was nearly deafening.</p>

<p>In this moment, I truly witnessed the heart of the Drupal community in action - this amazing tool could not exist without a number of developers carefully crafting code in accordance with Drupal best practices, and countless generous individuals attentively reviewing the proposed changes. It really does take a village, and the good news is that it doesn’t require being a coding genius to help out.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/commiting-to-d8/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/commiting-to-d8/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Meet the ThinkShout Team at DrupalCon LA!</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>It’s that time of year again - that’s right, DrupalCon! We’re excited to visit sunny (and warm, and apparently very dry) Los Angeles this year for DrupalCon 2015. We might have to dust off our shorts for this one.</p>

<p>The location for this year’s conference holds a special place in our hearts, as we have a handful of awesome clients and partners (and some friends, too) that we can’t wait to see while we geek out about all things Drupal. As always, we’ll all be running around during this four day event, but here are all the specific places where you can catch up with us:</p>

<h2 id="exhibit-hall">Exhibit Hall##</h2>

<p>We’re partnering with our friends MailChimp at booth 800. Stop by for some cool swag, to talk shop, and learn about the exciting work we’re doing porting the MailChimp module to Drupal 8. We’re also hiring for <a href="http://thinkshout.com/careers/">several positions</a>, so if you’d like to meet face to face and get a better feel for what it would be like to join the ThinkShout team, come chat with us.</p>

<h2 id="official-sessions">Official Sessions##</h2>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/scaling-your-business-starts-right-spreadsheets-performance-metrics">Scaling Your Business Starts with the Right Spreadsheets: Performance Metrics</a><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/scaling-your-business-starts-right-spreadsheets-performance-metrics"> </a></p>

<p>Join ThinkShout’s Sean Larkin and Forum One’s Chris Wolz as they discuss tools and techniques for collaboration and management that will help you make better long-term decisions for your business.</p>

<p>Tuesday May 12th, 10:45-11:45am</p>

<p>Room: 502B - Lullabot</p>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/if-i-only-had-framework-creating-unified-digital-experience-across-3rd-party">If I Only Had a Frame(work): Crafting Experiences Across 3rd-Party Systems</a></p>

<p>Lev Tsypin and Brett Meyer will discuss creating and developing a create a cohesive experience across multiple platforms even when they aren’t all open source.</p>

<p>Wednesday May 13th, 1-2pm</p>

<p>Room: 515A - Phase 2</p>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/building-your-drupal-based-business-or-what-keeps-you-night">Building Your Drupal-Based Business, Or, What Keeps You Up at Night</a></p>

<p>This facilitated panel session will include ThinkShout’s own Sean Larkin, and will cover insights from agency owners on lessons learned, areas of focus, and what NOT to worry about. All that and some guidance on best practices, and ideas to sustain and support growth - with an active audience Q&amp;A to boot.</p>

<p>Wednesday May 13th, 2:15-3:15pm</p>

<p>Room: Petree C - Acquia</p>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/ballin-budget-how-create-great-design-without-breaking-bank">Ballin’ on a Budget: How to Create Great Design Without Breaking the Bank</a><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/ballin-budget-how-create-great-design-without-breaking-bank"> </a></p>

<p>Our Lead User Experience Designer, Josh Riggs, will give us the low-down on creating kick-ass designs for any budget by utilizing solid design fundamentals, great communication, and maybe a few tricks up the sleeve.</p>

<p>Thursday May 14th, 10:45-11:45am</p>

<p>Room: 501 - NewMedia</p>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/mailchimp-drupal-anatomy-successful-partnership">MailChimp and Drupal, The Anatomy of a Successful Partnership</a></p>

<p>In this Lightning Talk, ThinkShout CTO Lev Tsypin and MailChimp API guru Nathan Ranson will cover the evolution of MailChimp’s support for Drupal, the basics of how the integration works, and hint at what’s to come for Drupal 8.</p>

<p>Thursday May 14th, 1:15pm</p>

<p>Room: TBD</p>

<h2 id="birds-of-a-feather-bof">Birds of a Feather (BoF)##</h2>

<p>ThinkShout team members will also be leading a couple of great BoF sessions. We hope to see you there!</p>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/bofs/design-and-prototyping-methods-responsive-drupal-sites">Design and Prototyping Methods for Responsive Drupal Sites</a> with Josh Riggs (@joshriggs)</p>

<p>Tuesday May 12th, 10:45-11:45am</p>

<p>Room: 410 - The Cherry Hill Company</p>

<p><a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/bofs/integrating-drupal-salesforce">Integrating Drupal with Salesforce</a> with Tauno Hogue</p>

<p>Wednesday May 13th, 10:45-11:45am</p>

<p>Room: 505 - Chromatic</p>

<p>And finally, as we mentioned earlier, we’re excited about visiting LA this year because we’ll get a bit of face time with some of the great west coast clients and partners we’ve been working with over the last few years. We will be hosting a special happy hour reception celebrating these LA organizations and honoring one of our long-time clients and partners, the <a href="http://thinkshout.com/work/la-conservancy/">Los Angeles Conservancy</a>, with a donation from our team.</p>

<p>We hope to see you at DrupalCon this year. If you can’t make it, get in touch with us and we’ll fill you in on what you missed! You can also follow along on all the social networks: <a href="https://twitter.com/thinkshout">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ThinkShout">Facebook</a>, and <a href="https://instagram.com/thinkshout/">Instagram</a> - we’ll keep you posted!</p>

<p>To those of you heading down to LA, California or BUST!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/drupalcon-la/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/drupalcon-la/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Monkeying Around with D8</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<h2 id="leading-the-charge">Leading the Charge</h2>

<p>I have used A LOT of email marketing service providers over the years and my opinion of them was twofold: they were all similar and none of them were particularly great. Was it possible that this was just a category of business that would never be exciting or innovative? Was I destined to be a project manager who half-heartedly recommended whatever email service provider I was using most at the time to clients?</p>

<p><em>Enter the Chimp…</em></p>

<p>Despite its playful name, <a href="http://www.mailchimp.com">MailChimp</a> made a serious shift in a category that had always had potential but lacked a true champion. My first thought when I used the tool was that even if the feature set was identical to all its competitors, MailChimp’s user interface alone was what set it apart. But once I dug into its capabilities, I became a bona fide fan (dare I say ambassador) of the brand. From automated email workflows and slick segmentation capabilities, to the [Chimpadeedoo] (http://mailchimp.com/features/mobile-signup-forms/) tablet app that facilitates email sign-ups without an internet connection, MailChimp became the new king of the jungle.</p>

<p>Fast forward a few years, and here I am working at ThinkShout, MailChimp’s Drupal partner. We built and maintain the MailChimp Drupal module, which is used by nearly 22,000 websites.</p>

<p>If you are familiar with MailChimp’s motto - listen hard and change fast - (or if you just read the first couple paragraphs of this blog post), then it should come as no surprise that innovation is at the heart of MailChimp’s culture. With the release of Drupal 8 looming this Fall, MailChimp and ThinkShout saw a unique opportunity to lead the charge by porting one of the most popular email modules to be D8 compatible.</p>

<h2 id="the-only-way-through-it-is-through-it">The Only Way Through it is Through it</h2>

<p>Being a trailblazer isn’t easy, and MailChimp understood that pushing the envelope on D8 development would require a significant investment of time and resources. While the core MailChimp module is relatively simple, the bundled submodules are feature-rich and technically complex.</p>

<p>Let’s recap what the MailChimp module allows you to do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Any “object” in Drupal that has an email address, say a User, Contact, or even a Comment, can be automatically subscribed to a list and segmented based on other attributes, like their zip code.</li>
  <li>Display a list subscription status on an entity or a subscription form.</li>
  <li>Map Drupal Data, such as name and address, to merge fields in MailChimp.</li>
  <li>Create forms to allow site visitors to sign up for any Mailchimp List or combination of Lists.</li>
  <li>Create Pages, Blocks, or both to display forms.</li>
  <li>Create campaigns containing any Drupal entity, or entities, as content.</li>
  <li>Send campaigns created in Drupal through MailChimp or Drupal.</li>
  <li>View campaign statistics and email activity for all list subscribers.</li>
</ul>

<p>Luckily, one of the greatest aspects of our partnership with MailChimp is our shared passion for recognizing opportunity in challenges and giving back to the community. With that spirit, a couple of ThinkShout engineers dove in head first with the goal of porting the majority of the popular D7 module’s features over to D8 in time for a beta release at [DrupalCon LA] (https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015). During the process, they realized that the available Drupal 8 documentation wasn’t keeping up with the speedy pace of D8 development. Over the course of several weeks, our engineers updated documentation and created examples to make life (or at least development) a little easier for the next developer looking to create something similar.</p>

<h2 id="its-a-sprint-not-a-marathon">It’s a Sprint, Not a Marathon</h2>

<p>With the conference approaching, it was time to call on the ThinkShout village to help put the polish on the new module. Since nine heads are better than two when it comes to user testing and QA, we scheduled a sprint to focus our engineering department on providing that critical perspective needed at the end of a large development project.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/mailchimp_roadmap1.jpg" alt="mailchimp_roadmap1.jpg" /></p>

<p>During our afternoon sprint, our team ran a battery of tests (both human and automated) to document and resolve bugs. Our engineering staff has grown quite a bit recently, so the sprint also provided an opportunity for knowledge sharing about MailChimp and D8 development across the team. As a non-engineer fly on the wall, it was exciting to witness the energy at the sprint table, as bugs were closed and high-fives were thrown.</p>

<h2 id="the-future-is-now">The Future is Now</h2>

<p>So far, I’ve focused on what some of the challenges of early D8 development have been, and you’re surely wondering by now “So, what do you think about D8?” Short answer: we’re excited, and we think you should be, too.</p>

<p>Drupal 8 standardizes module development by enforcing PSR-4 compliant namespaces. Whereas D7 allows developers to dictate where a form or entity is placed, for example, D8 loads files in the correct path automatically. What does this mean for developers? Well, it means time saved by not having to search an entire codebase to find where the developer before you placed a form. And because this structure is more in line with general engineering practices, it will be easier for any developer to ramp up for Drupal development.</p>

<p>But the benefits aren’t just for developers. We are also excited about the efficiencies that will be created for our nonprofit clients. Not only do they stand to benefit from the streamlined development approach, but that shift in approach will also make it easier to find resources to maintain and enhance their sites.</p>

<h2 id="learn-more-about-the-new-mailchimp-module">Learn More About the New MailChimp Module</h2>

<p>Come and see us at [DrupalCon LA] (https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015), where our very own [Lev Tsypin] (http://thinkshout.com/team/lev/) will be giving a [lightning talk] (https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015/sessions/mailchimp-drupal-anatomy-successful-partnership) about the evolution of MailChimp’s support for Drupal, the basics of how the integration works, and a hint at what’s to come for Drupal 8. Don’t worry if you can’t make it to the talk because we’ll also be hanging out in the MailChimp booth. And if you spot one of us (you’ll recognize us by our ThinkShout hoodies), stop us! We’d love to chat about what we’ve learned about D8 and why were are excited for its release. Also, be sure to check out <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/category/mailchimp/">past blogs</a> we’ve written about our work on the MailChimp module.</p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/mailchimp-d8-sprint/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/05/mailchimp-d8-sprint/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Drupal and Salesforce Integrations Get Some (Data) Integrity</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Hot on the heels of our <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/01/reimagined-sprints-redhen-raiser/">all-hands-on-deck sprint to release</a> <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen_raiser">RedHen Raiser</a>, we decided to change gears to focus on some of our marquee open source contributions, namely the <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/salesforce">Salesforce Suite</a>.</p>

<p>The Salesforce Suite has been around since Drupal 5 and it’s evolved quite a bit in order to keep up with the ever-changing <a href="http://salesforce.com">Salesforce</a> and Drupal landscapes. Several years ago, we found ourselves relying heavily upon the Salesforce Suite for our Salesforce-Drupal integrations. But there came a point where we realized the module could no longer keep up with our needs. So we, in collaboration with the maintainers of the module at the time, set out to rewrite the suite for Drupal 7.</p>

<p>We completely rewrote the module, leveraging Drupal’s entity architecture, Salesforce’s REST API, and OAUTH for authentication. We also added much-needed features such as a completely new user experience, the ability to synchronize <em>any</em> Drupal and Salesforce objects, and a number of performance enhancements. This was a heck of an undertaking, and there were dozens of other improvements we made to the suite that you can read about in this <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2012/11/lev/salesforce-rest-oauth/">blog post</a>. We’ve maintained this module ever since and have endeavored to add new features and enhancements as they become necessary. We realized this winter that it was time for yet another batch of improvements as the complexity and scale of our integrations has grown.</p>

<p>In addition to over 150 performance enhancements and bug fixes, this release features an all new Drupal entity mapping system which shows a log of all synchronization activity, including any errors. You can now see a log entry for every attempted data synchronization. If there’s a problem, the log will tell you where it is and why it’s an issue. There’s now a whole interface designed to help you pinpoint where these issues are so you can solve them quickly.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/salesforce-activity.png" alt="Salesforce Activity" /></p>

<p>Administrators can even manually create or edit a connection between Drupal and Salesforce objects. Before this update, the only way to connect two objects was to create the mapping and then wait for an object to be updated or created in either Drupal or Salesforce. Now you can just enter the Salesforce ID and you’re all set.</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/salesforce-edit.png" alt="Salesforce Edit Mapping" /></p>

<p>Take the following example to understand why these improvements are so critical. Say that your constituents are volunteering through your Drupal site using the <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/registration">Registration module</a>. The contacts are created or updated in <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen">RedHen</a> and then synced to Salesforce. For some reason, you can see the new volunteers in Drupal, but they are not showing in Salesforce. It used to be that the only clue to a problem was buried in the error log. Now, all you have to do is go to the RedHen contact record, and then click “Salesforce activity,” and you’ll see a record of the attempted sync and an explanation of why it failed. Furthermore, you can manually connect the contact to Salesforce by entering the Salesforce ID.</p>

<p>Finally, you can now delete existing mappings, or map to an entirely different content type. The bottom line is that module users have more control of, and insights into, how their data syncs to Salesforce. You can <a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/2452127">download version 7.x-3.1</a> from Drupal.org and experience these improvements for yourself.</p>

<p>We’ve been hard at work polishing several other of our modules and tools, like the RedHen suite and Entity Registration, which also saw new releases. We’ll tell you more about what you can expect from those new versions in our upcoming blogs.</p>

<p>Want to chat about our module work at <a href="https://events.drupal.org/losangeles2015">DrupalCon</a> in LA? You can find us hanging out with our friends from <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/category/mailchimp/">MailChimp</a> at their booth. We’d love to talk to you more about what we’re working on.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 13:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/04/salesforce-new-features/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/04/salesforce-new-features/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>The Power of a Collaborative Community</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p><em>Originally published on <a href="http://www.nten.org/articles/2014/my-year-in-drupal-the-power-of-a-collaborative-community">NTEN.org</a> on December 10th, 2014.</em></p>

<p><strong>My Year in Drupal</strong></p>

<p>I’ve been fortunate to attend some of the biggest Drupal events in the U.S., and I always walk away from them with plenty of food for thought. Months ago, NTEN afforded me the space here to sing the Drupal community’s praises and I haven’t stopped since. I’m constantly reminded of how much I value its existence. More recently, I flew down to San Francisco to take part in the Nonprofit Summit at BADCamp that I’d co-coordinated, where I got to hear from the Bay Area folks about Drupal and nonprofits in their neck of the woods.</p>

<p><strong>Once Again, The Drupal Community is Awesome</strong></p>

<p>Events like BADCamp remind of the value of discussion and the exchange of ideas. Struggling to find a solution? Look to your community. One of the reasons I so appreciate the Drupal community specifically is how wonderfully they collaborate. Out of resources? Speak up in your discussion group or start a thread on a forum and watch the outpouring of support and ideas. The next thing you know, you’re looking at a list of new modules and tools that you’ve never heard of, and they might be exactly what your site needs.</p>

<p>There’s something wonderfully exciting about being in a room full of people with the same idea: <em>let’s create and use technology to help people</em>. This kind of collaborative atmosphere can make even the tallest of technological hurdles seem surmountable. If you enjoy events like BADCamp for networking and learning about nonprofit tech, then there are a couple of other events you’ll want to put on your calendar.</p>

<p><strong>NYC Camp</strong></p>

<p>If you are a fan of BADCamp, then <a href="http://nyccamp.org/">NYC Camp</a> is just your speed. It’s a free, week-long Drupal conference in New York City from March 16-22, 2015. There’s also a nonprofit summit on the Friday of that week, which you definitely won’t want to miss.</p>

<p><strong>Drupal Day at NTC</strong></p>

<p>For the last three years, we’ve been coordinating <a href="http://myntc.nten.org/eventdetails/precon/drupal">Drupal Day</a> at NTEN’s Nonprofit Technology Conference, so I may be a little biased when I say this is an excellent opportunity to learn more about Drupal for nonprofits. You’ll hear from Drupal experts as well as nonprofit technologists sharing their Drupal stories and successes. This is a chance to learn about what exactly goes into building a Drupal site and how you can leverage it to further your organization’s mission with case study-style presentations throughout the day. But it’s not just about code - it’s about everything else that goes into making a successful website: content strategy, user experience, responsive design, infrastructure, the whole nine yards. If you’re curious about taking that first step toward Drupal, this event is a great place to start - and get ready for a whole lot of excellent information.</p>

<p><em>This year, join us on March 3rd, the day before NTC, in Austin, Texas. Registration for Drupal Day is free when you purchase a ticket to NTC. If you’ve already registered for the NTC, but didn’t sign up for Drupal Day, never fear - just contact NTEN event staff and ask to be put on the registration list.</em></p>

<p><strong>Never Stop Learning</strong></p>

<p>I never cease to be amazed at how much I still have left to learn. I know I’ll never truly be done learning, as is the nature of technology. It’s always in motion, always evolving with us and our ideas. I’m constantly surprised by even the simplest of tools. For instance, if you’re organizing a meetup or hosting a summit of your own, it’s a great idea to provide attendees with a site for collective notes, like and etherpad. This is especially helpful if you have multiple sessions happening concurrently. That way, even if your attendees can’t attend every session, they can read their peers’ notes. One of the most rewarding parts of the BADCamp Nonprofit Summit for me was opening up our once-blank etherpad after the summit and finding pages and pages of notes, tools, and URLs from discussions throughout the day. In a matter of hours, we created an amazing nonprofit tech resource.</p>

<p>I really hope you’ll take the time to immerse yourself in a Drupal Camp or Drupal-themed event and really immerse yourself in this community. These camps are often highly affordable (or free, in the case of BADCamp and NYC Camp), so it’s just a matter of finding one near you. Need help with that part? <a href="http://buildamodule.com/drupal-camps-calendar">Build-a-Module’s</a> got you covered. Yes, that same site I mentioned months ago offers online Drupal training as well as a calendar of Drupal events all over the world.</p>

<p>I also hope those of you who are NTC-bound will consider adding Drupal Day to your schedule - it’s a wonderful introduction to the Drupal Community. Even if you can’t make it to NTC or Drupal Day, take a chance on a Drupal Summit. Meet new peers, exchange ideas and concerns, and join in on this ongoing conversation. When you speak up, you become part of the change we all need to make this community, and Drupal, even better.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/01/collaborative-community/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/01/collaborative-community/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
