<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/nonprofit-tech/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>Meet the ThinkShout Team at DrupalCon Baltimore</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>We’re packing our bags for Baltimore and polishing up our slide decks for DrupalCon! We’re so excited to join the Drupal community for a full week of Drupal-y things. We’ve got some great content planned for this year’s conference, and we’re very excited to share it with you all - here’s what you need to know:</p>

<h2 id="exhibit-hall">Exhibit Hall</h2>

<p>The ThinkShout Headquarters this year is <strong>booth 432</strong>! We’ll be giving away free t-shirts and raffling off an Amazon Echo. You can enter to win for the low, low price of one business card. If you have any questions about <a href="https://thinkshout.com/work/">our work</a>, current available <a href="https://thinkshout.com/careers/">job opportunities</a>, or what the <a href="https://isitraining.in/Portland">weather’s like in Portland</a> (spoiler: it’s probably raining), stop by - we’d love to chat with you!</p>

<h2 id="thinkshout-sessions">ThinkShout Sessions</h2>

<p>The ThinkShout team has two sessions in the DrupalCon agenda this year. We’re also very excited to be leading a discussion in our first DrupalCon Nonprofit Summit. Take a look at our lineup and mark your calendars</p>

<p>“<a href="https://events.drupal.org/baltimore2017/nonprofit-summit">Rapid Response Campaigns &amp; Digital Tools</a>” - Monday (4/24), 12:30 - 1:15pm, Nonprofit Summit</p>

<p>The news cycle doesn’t stop, and your website must help you respond to emergencies, not act as a barrier. Drupal can help you react quickly, in concert with your other channels, to turn current events into opportunities to spread your message and further your mission. In this breakout session, Brett Meyer and Lev Tsypin will talk about the tools you have at your disposal in Drupal, scenarios that call for rapid response solutions and how to implement them, and strategies that will help you turn these situations into lasting engagement with your constituents.</p>

<p>“<a href="https://events.drupal.org/baltimore2017/sessions/demystifying-rendered-content-drupal-8-twig-files">Demystifying Rendered Content in Drupal 8 Twig Files</a>” - Tuesday (4/25), 3:45 - 4:45pm</p>

<p>Amy Vaillancourt-Sals is going to show you the ins and outs of Twig! <a href="http://twig.sensiolabs.org/">Twig</a> is a robust and elegant template engine for PHP. It’s lightweight, fairly quick to pick up, very readable, and it grants users ultimate control over the markup, including wrapping elements and rendering exactly the output you need. In this session, you’ll learn about the debugging process of sorting through twig variables, using xdebug in PHPStorm, the other helpful debugging tools at your disposal, plus common patterns Amy found helpful for rendering content in twig files.</p>

<p>“<a href="https://events.drupal.org/baltimore2017/sessions/content-strategy-popular-culture-part-deux">Content Strategy in Popular Culture, Part Deux</a>” - Thursday (4/27), 10:45 - 11:45am</p>

<p>Brett Meyer’s got a sequel to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sJxtCPRde4k">his session from DrupalCon New Orleans</a>. Another year, another array of pop culture obsessions to examine and apply to the work we do. By exploring how crucial aspects of content strategy play out in movies, music, comic books, and video games, we’ll continue to expand the palette of language we can use to explain and convince more people about the importance of content strategy online, and ensure they understand that it’s not just vital, but fun as well.</p>

<h2 id="lets-chat">Let’s Chat</h2>

<p>If you’d like to schedule some time to chat with us in advance, drop us a line via our <a href="https://thinkshout.com/contact/">contact form</a>. We’d be happy to meet up with you in Baltimore!</p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/04/meet-thinkshout-at-drupalcon-baltimore/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/04/meet-thinkshout-at-drupalcon-baltimore/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>See You at the NTC</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>The Nonprofit Technology Conference is just around the corner, and we’re hard at work making those final preparations for our trip to D.C. We have some exciting things in store for you this year, so mark your calendars!</p>

<h2 id="drupal-salon">Drupal Salon</h2>

<p>This year, we’re honored to coordinate the first ever Drupal Salon at the NTC. In lieu of the traditional pre-conference days as we’ve done in previous years, NTEN set aside space and time for subject matter experts to present nine twenty-minute-long talks on all things Drupal on Thursday, March 23rd. These talks will take place as part of the formal NTC schedule, and sessions can be viewed in the <a href="https://www.nten.org/ntc/program/agenda/">Wordpress &amp; Drupal Salon tracks on the NTC site</a>.</p>

<p>We’re excited to have experts from the Southern Poverty Law Center, Shatterproof, and the Center for Strategic and International Studies share their Drupal insight and experiences. ThinkShout will also be providing one-on-one consulting at our Drupal Salon table, so bring us all of your Drupal questions! Drupal hosting providers Pantheon and Acquia will also be on hand to tackle whatever Drupal hosting questions you may have.</p>

<p>We hope you’ll be able to join us! Here’s what we’ll be talking about:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/stories-that-matter-how-the-splc-responded-to-the-2016-election/">Stories that Matter: How the SPLC Responded to the 2016 Election</a>” - Alex Amend, Digital Media Director (The Southern Poverty Law Center)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/rapid-response-options-in-drupal/">Rapid Response Options in Drupal</a>” - Eric Paxton, Senior Front End Engineer (ThinkShout)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/drupal-powered-digital-storytelling/">Drupal-Powered Digital Storytelling</a>” - Brett Meyer, Director of Strategy (ThinkShout)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/drupal-as-a-hub-custom-integrations-for-csis/">Drupal as a Hub: Custom Integrations for CSIS</a>” - Ian Gottesman, Chief Information Officer (CSIS)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/integrating-drupal-and-salesforce/">Integrating Drupal and Salesforce</a>” - Lev Tsypin, Founder &amp; CEO (ThinkShout)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/event-registration-with-drupal/">Event Registration with Drupal</a>” - Gabe Carleton-Barnes, Engineering Manager (ThinkShout)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/how-shatterproof-fights-addiction-with-compelling-content/">How Shatterproof Fights Addiction with Compelling Content</a>” - Anthony Della Camera, Technology Director &amp; Jessica Ishikawa, Interactive Designer (Shatterproof)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/content-modeling-for-drupal-based-websites/">Content Modeling for Drupal-based Websites</a>” - Brett Meyer, Director of Strategy (ThinkShout)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/leveraging-drupal-in-your-marketing-strategies/">Leveraging Drupal in Your Marketing Strategies</a>” - Natania LeClerc, Senior Digital Engagement Strategist (ThinkShout)</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>We’re confident that the Drupal Salon sessions will have a little something for everyone, and we look forward to connecting with the nonprofit community with this new format.</p>

<h2 id="meet-the-thinkshout-team">Meet the ThinkShout Team</h2>

<p>Be sure to catch our team session on March 23rd, as well!</p>

<ul>
  <li>“<a href="https://www.nten.org/session/how-to-learn-to-stop-worrying-and-love-your-digital-agency/">How to Learn to Stop Worrying and Love Your Digital Agency</a>” - Alex Amend (Southern Poverty Law Center), Michele Kayal (Relief International), Alex MacMillan (ThinkShout), and Lev Tsypin (ThinkShout)</li>
</ul>

<p>The ThinkShout team will have a presence in the Exhibit Hall this year, of course. Stop by our booth (#501) and chat; we’ll be debuting brand new t-shirts and we’re excited to share them with you all (for free)! This is a great opportunity to learn more about our work and the organizations we partner with. We’re also available to talk about anything B Corp related, so send those questions our way!</p>

<p>If you’d like to schedule a time to meet with our staff at the NTC in advance, drop us a line through our <a href="https://thinkshout.com/contact/">contact form</a>. See you in the capitol!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/03/thinkshout-at-the-2017-ntc/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/03/thinkshout-at-the-2017-ntc/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Your Year-End Plan - It's Never Too Early to Start</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>If you’re putting off planning your year-end campaign in October, get ready to put in a lot of overtime.</p>

<p>You should ideally start thinking about your year-end campaign in the summer. This means considering campaign themes, stories, mapping out capacity, channel integration options, segmentation and tracking — not to mention how all of this will coincide (or not) with your plans for #GivingTuesday. Yes, it cannot be ignored - #GivingTuesday is a must for your year-end strategy.</p>

<p>So much rides on the last month (or in some cases, the last week) of the year for just about all   nonprofit organizations. It’s when people are the most generous and want to get their last tax-deductible gift in. But with all the other worthy causes out there looking to get in front of these ready and willing donors, how do you rise above the noise and get people to pay attention to you and your cause?</p>

<h2 id="set-the-stage">Set the Stage</h2>

<p>Before you make the knee-jerk decision to use Twitter, SnapChat or Facebook Live, you should know the story you want to tell. It also helps if you know who your audience is and where they are. Your time is precious, so you should focus it where you can leverage the best audience.</p>

<p>When we go about planning a campaign for our partners at ThinkShout, we typically start by looking at the analytics. It helps to have numbers that back up your decisions. With solid data to tell you the type of content on your site that draws in visitors, you can then brainstorm with your team to help determine what your story should be, and in which channels it is most likely to thrive.</p>

<p>It also helps to create a communications calendar; one that not only includes emails and direct mail drop dates, but also what your home page hero image will be from one month/week to the next, and when to plan some social posts versus leaving some breathing room for more organic, timely information. If applicable, you may even want to include when and where you plan to run digital/print ads.</p>

<p>Really think outside the box to reach people at any stage of their relationship with you.</p>

<h2 id="the-strategy">The Strategy</h2>

<p>The emails you send to your supporters carry as much importance as the effort you put into them. If you send emails just for the sake of sending them, that’s not a good reason to reach out to someone who has entrusted you with their contact information. <a href="http://mrbenchmarks.com/">Email open rates are already on the decline industry-wide</a>. Sending something that lacks value to your supporters will only make that trend catch on.</p>

<p>By utilizing the most compelling way to let your story unfold, and carrying that narrative into multiple channels in an effective way, you will inspire people to want to share it and spread the word – and ultimately – give.</p>

<h2 id="extras">Extras</h2>

<p>Lightboxes and homepage takeovers - you think they’re tacky, but there’s a reason why more and more nonprofits are utilizing these tactics at year-end and intermittently throughout the year: because <a href="http://npengage.com/nonprofit-marketing/why-pop-ups-should-be-part-of-your-online-fundraising/">they work</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/your-year-end-plan-1.png" alt="Email acquisition lightbox as seen on Travel Oregon website" /><span class="caption"><i class="fa fa-caret-up"></i>Email acquisition lightbox on Travel Oregon website - <a href="http://www.traveloregon.com">www.traveloregon.com</a> </span></p>

<p>I know what you’re thinking, ‘lightboxes and popups are aggressive and I hate them!’ …but lightboxes are not an all-or-none part of your strategy. They can be programmed to appear on a user’s first visit and then never again, or whatever you are comfortable starting with. As you grow to understand your audience more, that will dictate the behavior you set for your lightbox overlay.</p>

<h2 id="dont-forget-to-measure">Don’t Forget to Measure</h2>

<p>After putting all this effort into planning, segmenting, and designing, how will you know the strategy worked? How will you know if the lightbox brought in an extra 40% of funds or if it was the URL in the banner ads you had running? Spend some of this time early on setting up unique tracking links, separate donation forms, or other methods to ensure you can identify sources of donation traffic.</p>

<p>It’s worth noting that the channel of action does not always indicate the source of inspiration for the gift. What I mean is, someone can be exposed to your social media posts, your emails, some online banner ads – but after receiving your winter newsletter, they decide to go online and make a gift. Hard to tell, right? There will always be some degree of ‘guessing’ (for now, anyway). Mapping results as much as you are able is what proves the value of your investment to your leadership team and Board.</p>

<h2 id="giving-tuesday">Giving Tuesday</h2>

<p>The strategies outlined above for your year-end campaign should ideally also be applied to the 24-hour whirlwind that is #GivingTuesday. Yes, it may seem a waste of resources to put so much effort and work into a single day of giving, but in the four years that it’s been running, studies have found that #GivingTuesday does not cannibalize gifts, in fact it adds to your bottom line.</p>

<p>If you do it right, that whirlwind could be your next windfall. Here are some things you should consider:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Swap out the creative/offer on your lightbox, your hero image, and all social channels to match the creative theme of the day</li>
  <li>Create a unique donation form/URL for tracking purposes</li>
  <li>Create 2-5 emails to promote: Teaser message dropping the day before; Day-of email (sent in the morning); Mid-day update; Last chance message later in the day; Stewardship/recap email the day after.</li>
  <li>Draft updates for social channels - have these ready to go but be flexible in case something awesome happens that you need to react to in the moment. Social needs to be organic. Canned messages are ok, but allow yourself the freedom to change gears in case you get a large gift or a match offer, etc.</li>
</ul>

<p>This might seem like a lot of work. That’s because it is! But with some careful planning, you can set yourself up for success. And if this still seems like a lot to work out, let us know. We’d love to hear how we can help you achieve your year-end goals.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/08/your-year-end-plan/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/08/your-year-end-plan/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Roadmap to Retention</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>We’ve talked about <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/03/rethinking-strategies-for-online-donor-acquisition/">ways to attract and on-board new supporters</a>. Maybe you’ve started testing some of those strategies and set up a lightbox. That was a lot of hard work! Let’s take a break…</p>

<p>… and talk about how to cultivate those newbies so they don’t abandon ship. It’s called the <a href="http://www.pamelagrow.com/7256/are-you-taking-advantage-of-the-honeymoon-phase-in-your-nonprofit-marketing/">honeymoon phase</a>, and you need to take advantage of it while those contacts are feeling warm and fuzzy about supporting you.</p>

<p>Let’s back up a few steps. Think about the people in your life. You have tertiary contacts - people that are friends of friends, or vague acquaintances that you might see at a party and never again. Then, there are closer contacts – maybe they’re coworkers or people from class. You know them on the surface; some of their hobbies, general interests. You might even connect with them on LinkedIn, maybe Facebook. Then there are our closer friends; these are individuals you have a phone number and personal email for. They aren’t blocked from any of your social media accounts and you text each other frequently. You know each other on a deeper level and rarely find cause for disagreement.</p>

<p>This isn’t an exact parallel to the donor-relationship, but you get the idea. You want that donor to be happy to hear from you and for there to be a mutual appreciation. How can you create that type of relationship and feeling in this new contact?</p>

<p>Spoiler alert: there’s no ultimate, magic solution. You have to test and see what works for your audience. This won’t be the last time you hear me say this, either. The only way to determine what works is to fail early and often… until you don’t. The only way to do that is to test.</p>

<p>What we can do however is provide some basic guidance and make recommendations based on what we in the fundraising community have seen work for us.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Content: Keep it fresh and up to date on your website - give people a reason to keep coming back to you. This isn’t just of benefit to donors, by the way – refreshing content is good for Google crawlers. They’re responsible for presenting the best content in search results to end users. If your site or home page hasn’t been refreshed in some time, Google may not give you top billing in the search results. There’s a lot more that goes into SEO, but that’s a topic for another time. Bottom line is, don’t let things get stale.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It’s like the theme from the Golden Girls, “Thank you for being a friend” er, donor: Set up a stewardship series to be sure you thank your supporters for being awesome. You can’t do the vital work for your cause without them, so show your appreciation! All this money you’ve been asking people for is presumably going towards something good and valuable, share those successes – and make your donors the star.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Know your audience: Give them every opportunity to engage with you in the way(s) they want on the platforms they choose. You know your audience best (if not, we need to have a talk about that). If your file is comprised of an older demographic, you may want to hold off on a major investment in a social media push. Alternatively, if you have a younger audience of advocates, they might be more interested in events and ways they can actively participate with your cause online. Again: Know your audience.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Track your results: look for patterns (or direct feedback from contacts) in communication preferences. Monitor what gets the best responses as well as what doesn’t so you know what to repeat (or avoid) in the future, and build off those successes.</li>
  <li>Basically, maintain contact in valuable, meaningful ways. The major reason why people stop supporting an organization, outside of death or changes to one’s financial situation, is due to poor communication. <a href="https://i0.wp.com/fundraisingcoach.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/GuestPost-Jay-Love-Why-Donors-Stop-Their-Support.png">This infographic</a> from Bloomerang is a couple years old, but still highly relevant:</li>
</ul>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/retention-info.png" alt="retention-info.png" /></p>

<p>Here are the top reasons why you’re really losing donors:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Thought the charity did not need them - 5%</li>
  <li>No information on how monies were used - 8%</li>
  <li>No memory of supporting - 9%</li>
  <li>Never thanked for donating - 13%</li>
  <li>Poor service or communication - 18%</li>
</ol>

<p>The good news? It’s totally within your control to make sure you don’t succumb to these pitfalls. Unsure of where to start with your content curation or how to create an editorial calendar everyone in your organization can use? The Lightbox Collaborative has put together a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/15jQdv2ITgbUjUZ7U9i2ZEH30aiNiBk95RzX4arE4rAw/edit#gid=0">workbook</a> that’s a great starting point. Still not sure what to make of all of this? We can help – contact us to learn more about our strategic offerings and how we can put you on the roadmap to retention.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/05/roadmap-to-retention/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/05/roadmap-to-retention/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Rethinking Strategies for Online Donor Acquisition</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>File attrition is (unfortunately) a completely normal part of nonprofit life, and list churn – aka attrition or loss of subscribers/donors – happens to even the most seasoned cultivation programs. On average, organizations see a monthly churn rate of <a href="http://www.mrbenchmarks.com/" target="_blank">1.7%</a>. That’s why you must create additional opportunities to grow your file and bring more supporters on board.</p>

<p>Some online approaches have been around for a while, some are relatively new, and lastly (but certainly not least) there are some you’d be better off without.</p>

<p>Before we get to the good stuff, it’s important to note that if you want to grow your file, you need to have systems in place to properly welcome these new contacts. You wouldn’t welcome a guest to your home and neglect to show them where the restroom is or where you keep your coffee cups, right? The same goes for new email addresses: you wouldn’t drop them into the communication stream with your next newsletter or fundraising appeal… and it isn’t the way online audiences expect you to interact with them today.</p>

<p>At minimum, prepare an autoresponder message to confirm the user’s registration.</p>

<p>Want to take it a step further? Set up a <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/NonprofitWebinars/the-power-of-the-welcome-series" target="_blank">Welcome Series</a> and go into greater detail about what the user can expect to learn and receive from your organization.</p>

<p>Now, onto the nitty gritty:</p>

<h3 id="google-adwords">Google AdWords</h3>

<p>If you don’t have a <a href="https://www.google.com/intl/ALL/grants" target="_blank">Google Grant</a>, apply for one today (seriously, right after you finish reading this article). Through Google for Nonprofits, you can apply for an Ad Grant that is essentially $10k in in-kind dollars you can use towards advertising on Google.</p>

<p>There are limitations to this advertising method: Ads are text-based, and because of the cap on the cost per click (CPC) there will be some keywords you may not be able to utilize. But overall, it’s an incredible resource available to your organization <a href="https://support.google.com/nonprofits/answer/3215869?hl=en-CA&amp;ref_topic=3247288" target="_blank">if it’s a qualifying 501(c)(3)</a>.</p>

<p>If closely monitored and executed, your organization will gain prime positioning in the search results when people type in a keyword related to your organization. It’s free advertising dollars available to you each month, and well worth the time.</p>

<h3 id="banner-ads">Banner Ads</h3>

<p>The utilization of banner ads and remarketing is growing in popularity (and necessity). In fact, the <a href="http://www.mrbenchmarks.com/" target="_blank"> 2015 Benchmarks Report </a> found that 50% of the organizations surveyed invested in some form of retargeting, while 66% invested in text/display ads. There is definitely stiff competition for visibility and getting your cause in front of the eyes of potential supporters.</p>

<p>So what is retargeting? Well, you’ve most likely experienced it already.  You’re shopping on Amazon, minding your own business, but you decide not to buy those Marc Jacobs shoes today. Before you know it, you’re killing time on Facebook at lunch and you see an ad for those shoes off to the side with those other, creepily relevant ads. Slowly, those shoes become peppered into your online experience wherever you go. This somewhat annoying but effective tactic is called remarketing.</p>

<p>And nonprofits do it, too, with <a href="http://www.nonprofitpro.com/article/finding-your-direct-mail-fundraising-donors-online/2/" target="_blank"> varying degrees of success</a>.</p>

<p>Just as you want to sync your direct mail and online marketing pieces, display ads and remarketing can help to further saturate your potential supporters and convince them to join your cause. Besides, the majority of first time visitors to your site won’t make a gift. Retargeting gives them the opportunity to come back and remedy that mistake(!) –and also helps boost brand recognition.</p>

<h3 id="social-advertising">Social Advertising</h3>

<p>You can also extend retargeting into social channels.</p>

<p>Personally, I think the verdict is still out on fundraising through social media. It is, at best, a reinforcement channel and an opportunity for additional engagement. As an acquisition channel, however, people who follow your cause on social outlets are, typically, warm prospects (if they aren’t already diligent supporters). Those relationships are important to maintain.</p>

<p>Providing quality content that an end user will want to engage with is of utmost importance – but giving them a reason to leave Facebook and go to your website is tantamount to the holy grail.</p>

<p>If you can determine what your audience identifies as high-value content, and only make said content available behind the wall of an email address exchange, you may be able to grow that file in no time.</p>

<p>Another common approach is a pledge call-to-action. I don’t mean pledge in the monetary sense; rather “sign our pledge to end hunger” or “sign our pledge to find a cure for X.” (Ideally, this action would also be tied to social sharing opportunities so that your new supporter can recruit on your behalf). The supporter “signs” the pledge by entering their email address.</p>

<p>There are also benefits to tossing some advertising dollars toward promoted posts on Facebook. Check out how <a href="http://www.networkforgood.com/nonprofitblog/heres-the-best-way-to-fundraise-on-facebook/?utm_source=feedblitz&amp;utm_medium=FeedBlitzRss&amp;utm_campaign=katyasnon-profitmarketingblog" target="_blank"> Healing Waters</a> improved their results for #GivingTuesday with minimum fuss.</p>

<p>If you get the timing right, and know the type of content your audience is likely to engage with, you can increase your brand awareness while growing your file.</p>

<h3 id="lightboxslide-in-aka-a-popup">Lightbox/Slide-In (AKA a popup)</h3>

<p>The general reaction I get when I suggest implementing a lightbox/popup as a means to collect names or donations is for everyone in the room to recoil in horror. But if deployed strategically and when it makes sense, site visitors won’t have an adverse reaction to it. In fact, they’ll be glad you made it easier for them to find what they’re looking for.</p>

<p>You can deploy a lightbox with email signup fields on your homepage. Or, with some minimal sleuthing of your analytics data, you can identify the high-engagement pages on your site and launch a slide-in. Maybe you have a number of informative articles on disease prevention or early detection (for example). While someone is reading said article, a slide-in appears in the lower right corner: “Want to receive more vital information and updates like what you’re reading now? Sign up today.”</p>

<p>It’s all in how you position it. If you’re making their life easier, they won’t mind. But if you constantly interrupt their experience on every page, you’re more likely to receive a negative reaction. (So, don’t do that!)</p>

<p>All of the above recommendations should be paired with a Welcome Series or autoresponder once the submission form has processed. These methods all take some time to plan and deploy.</p>

<p>So, where should you not focus your energy?</p>

<h3 id="buyingrenting-email-lists">Buying/Renting Email Lists</h3>

<p>This often functions through a third party vendor, who will email (on your behalf) a file of hundreds (sometimes thousands) of emails they have identified as having an affinity to your cause. Your organization only gets the names if someone makes a gift or opts in through the vendor’s system.</p>

<p>This method is not only rather expensive, but it rarely (if ever) yields a return worth the investment. That’s not surprising: imagine how you would react to an email in your inbox that you know you didn’t sign up for… from an organization you have never heard of or been involved with. That’s an immediate swipe/delete.</p>

<p>Hubspot did a write-up on <a href="http://blog.hubspot.com/blog/tabid/6307/bid/32892/Why-Purchasing-Email-Lists-Is-Always-a-Bad-Idea.aspx" target="_blank"> why buying a list is a bad idea</a> should you need to bolster your argument to anyone who isn’t convinced.</p>

<p>So, focus on setting up the infrastructure to properly introduce new contacts into your organization, make them feel like they’re a part of something special with a welcome series. Then test, tweak, and re-test some of these methods to see what works best for you.</p>

<p>Have you tried any of these approaches to acquiring email addresses? Share with us what’s worked for you!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/03/rethinking-strategies-for-online-donor-acquisition/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2016/03/rethinking-strategies-for-online-donor-acquisition/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>The Small Business of Open Source</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>This summer, ThinkShout was named the <a href="http://www.bizjournals.com/portland/gallery/43111?s=image_gallery&amp;img_no=87&amp;s=image_gallery&amp;img_no=87">9th Fastest Growing Private Company in Portland, Oregon</a>. Admittedly, this came as sort of a shock to me and Lev. Over three and a half years, we’ve grown the company from two dudes renting desks in an incubator space to a full-time team of 17 professionals averaging 10 years of experience each. But most of the time, it doesn’t feel like we’ve come up with any secret sauce for running a successful business. We try to listen to our employees and our peers in the industry. We partner with nonprofit clients trying to make the world a better place, and we do our best to treat them with integrity in all aspects of our work - from our design and engineering practices to our approach to project management and our billing process.</p>

<p>Perhaps there are a few things that we do particularly well. We win our fair share of work in <em>coopetition</em> with our peers in the nonprofit tech industry. But then again, in talking with our friends at ZivTech, Gorton Studios, Aten Design Group, Jackson River, Forum One Communications, and others, what we consistently hear is that there is more than enough work to go around in the world of <em>technology for good</em>.</p>

<p>How is that? What are the mechanics of <strong>“the small business of open source”</strong> that work for all these firms and, more importantly, for their customers?</p>

<p>You could tackle this question from a number of angles. Conventional wisdom suggests that the business value of open source, both in the for-profit and nonprofit sectors, is simply: <em>you get a lot of stuff for free</em>. This is true. With open source, you avoid licensing fees. With an open source platform such as Drupal, you can pick and choose among literally tens of thousands of free tools and extensions.</p>

<p>But this perspective speaks only to open source’s initial customer appeal. It speaks to the coarse outlines of the sales cycle of open source. You can’t just build a sustainable business off the idea that a platform like Drupal provides a lot of stuff for free.</p>

<p>So, what is the guiding principle of growing a small business around open source? For us, it boils down to:</p>

<p><strong>Our customers benefit tremendously from their own contributions to open source.</strong></p>

<p>Put a bit more bluntly:</p>

<p><strong>Our customers benefit from <em>paying us to give away their code</em></strong>.</p>

<p>To illustrate this point, I’d like to run through some of our numbers as a small business of open source. The following statistics are relative to the publication date of this blog post:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>ThinkShout’s team includes 8 engineers with a total of <a href="https://www.drupal.org/contribute/development">4,269 commits</a> to contributed modules hosted on Drupal.org.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>We actively maintain 24 contributed modules that represent over 100,000 lines of code.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The combined installation base of these modules (i.e., the aggregated number of websites using each of these modules) is over 42,000.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Interestingly, our staff has grown 750% from the end of our first quarter. The growth in adoption of our contributed tools by the community (1,400% since the end of Q1 2011) tracks closely with the growth of our quarterly revenues (1,300%).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/thinkshout-growth.png" alt="thinkshout-growth.png" /></p>

<p>Obviously, these statistics are only related anecdotally. On their own, they don’t prove that our open source contributions drive our success.</p>

<p>Still, it is interesting to look at some of the statistics around our client work:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Averaging the last four $80-$150K Drupal website projects we’ve completed, a typical project in this price range is made up of 36,289 lines of custom code and exported site configuration (excluding the theme, or the implementation of the graphic design).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In addition, most of these projects include the release of 1,000-5,000 lines of contributed code. In other words, clients who engage with us on these sorts of projects pay for us either to contribute back major features to a contributed module, or to release one or two stand-alone modules.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>But what’s most interesting is that each of these projects leverage at least 4 to 5 of the contributed modules that other clients have paid for on previous projects. Each leverages around 20,000 lines of contributed code that our team has written for similar use cases.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Of course, these statistics reflect the significant cost savings to our clients in going with an open source solution. They get <em>a lot of free stuff…</em></p>

<p>But more importantly, our clients benefit from becoming financially invested in the direction and cultivation of these open source projects. By becoming <em>committers</em>, they are ensured that their requirements will continue to be prioritized in the future development of the modules their website depend on. They benefit too by the tens, sometimes hundreds, of open source developers reviewing their contributed code for bug fixes and improvements.</p>

<p>Moreover, by releasing the code that powers their websites, our clients connect with other organizations with similar requirements who, in turn, will often contribute additional features to these projects over time. As a case in point, we released the <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/leaflet">Leaflet module</a>, a web-based mapping solution, on behalf of the Intertwine Alliance in the summer of 2011. The Alliance paid for the initial release, which included a modest yet highly-innovative feature set. Since then, 36 different Drupal developers have contributed code to improve the module, and over 4,500 websites have adopted it.</p>

<p>Similarly, we initially released <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/redhen">RedHen CRM</a>, a native CRM solution built entirely within Drupal, for a small cohort of nonprofits with similar needs. In this case, we actually got these nonprofits to work together to brainstorm and prioritize their CRM requirements. Pooling funding, this group helped us launch RedHen publicly in the spring of 2012. Since then, over a dozen of our clients have continued to invest in RedHen, and it has been adopted on over 850 websites around the world. Most impressively, those initial clients that funded our early work on RedHen continue to upgrade their sites with each new release, benefitting from hundreds of thousands of dollars of <em>free</em> development.</p>

<p>Client investments in open source present many less tangible benefits as well. While our developers are inspired to support our mission-driven nonprofit customers, they are particularly excited (and therefore, keenly focused) when their work leads to open source contributions. Not only does this lead to high-quality engineering, it helps reduce turnover among our engineering team, which can be costly for clients. Among our team’s contributors to Drupal, our average turnover is less than half of the industry standard in information technology.</p>

<p>For readers of this post who represent agencies that also contribute to open source, I’d be curious if your data and experience track to ours. Business and nonprofit readers whose teams have paid for open source contributions, I’d be curious to hear your stories as well. After all, open source is all about transparency, which we believe makes us a more effective business.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2014 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/09/small-business-of-nonprofits/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/09/small-business-of-nonprofits/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Nonprofit Website Benchmarks</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Your website is a unique snowflake with singular requirements. While there’s surely overlap, the make-up of your audience is different from every other site, because your mission – and the content you put on your website to support that mission – is different from every other nonprofit.</p>

<p>But you’ve probably wondered how your site compares to others. I know I’ve always wanted access to website benchmarks – some way to see if the trends I notice in our own dashboards are reflective of larger patterns.</p>

<p>Of course, <a href="http://www.thinkmetrics.com/benchmarks-for-websites.php">benchmarks can be dangerous</a>. If you obsess about them, the action becomes whatever the opposite of navel gazing is.</p>

<p>When you analyze the efficacy of your own website, you always need to <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/04/desire-paths/">consider it within the context of your own target audiences and organizational goals</a> instead of worrying that your overall bounce rate is 4% higher than the “average.”</p>

<p>After all, if your site has the profile of a news organization, with links to recent articles shared widely through third-party channels, you should expect a higher bounce rate: people come, consume, and leave. That might be okay! The goal of that content may have been to spread some news, not generate donations.</p>

<p>Benchmarks can inform us about larger trends, though, and it’s damned annoying that they’re so hard to find.</p>

<p>It’s been almost four years since Groundwire published its 2010 Website Benchmarks Report. (Fortunately, you can still <a href="http://alaskaconservation.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/Groundwire-Website-Benchmarks-Study-2010.pdf">download the PDF from a third-party site</a>.) Since then, Google has <a href="https://productforums.google.com/forum/#!topic/analytics/17NoDhOIv8A">discontinued its Analytics Benchmarks Report</a> – and even <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/sjsu-csa-offiers/REkmko8K9RQ/tSDtcqTrOMcJ">the semi-useful newsletter</a> that followed.</p>

<p>You can <a href="https://www.marketingsherpa.com/data/public/reports/benchmark-reports/EXCERPT-BMR-2013-Marketing-Analytics.pdf">order a $395 report from Marketing Sherpas</a> (PDF), which may or may not be helpful; I certainly didn’t buy it. <a href="http://www.kissmetrics.com">KISSmetrics</a> published <a href="https://blog.kissmetrics.com/bounce-rate/">an infographic about bounce rates</a> a couple of years ago with some interesting data… <a href="https://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/webanalytics/conversations/topics/6116">that may have come from a 2006 post to a Yahoo group</a>.</p>

<p>Pew Research recently released <a href="http://www.journalism.org/2014/03/13/social-search-direct/">an interesting study comparing news sites</a>, using aggregated data from ComScore. I love how they’ve analyzed visitor loyalty across segments, but rare is the nonprofit that’s going to share the content goals of CNN or NBC News.</p>

<p>On our side, there are a couple of stats of interest in the latest <a href="http://www.mrbenchmarks.com/">Benchmarks Study</a> from <a href="http://www.mrss.com">M+R</a> and <a href="http://www.nten.org">NTEN</a> and the <a href="https://www.blackbaud.com/nonprofit-resources/onlinemarketingstudy">2013 Online Marketing Benchmark Study for Nonprofits</a> from <a href="http://www.blackbaud.com">Blackbaud</a>, but they’re mostly focused on traffic growth and donation page conversions.</p>

<p>At ThinkShout, because we start almost all of our engagements by exploring how our client’s audiences use their current website, we felt it would be important to have some point of comparison. To facilitate discussion around questions like “How much do we need to worry about mobile?” or “How can we convert the influx of new visitors into engaged users?”, we’ve aggregated the data we have available to us.</p>

<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/a/thinkshout.com/spreadsheets/d/1xl8p1VKx4i6uG3kqmHmNdS6s4B6g2kmPIl9sKAtjHwA/edit#gid=0">It seems only fair to share some of it</a>.</p>

<p>This data is in no way reflective of the industry as whole, and it is very top-level. It represents fifteen organizations with diverse missions and traffic patterns, ranging from a few thousand sessions per month to more than 100,000. These are also generally organizations that have recognized the need to redesign their website.</p>

<p>With those caveats, we hope this data may help you understand that some of what you see in your own analytics may, in fact, be reflective of broader trends.</p>

<p>The following are three I see in the 37,000,000 <a href="https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/1006243?hl=en">pageviews</a> we have access to.</p>

<h3 id="search-is-the-ultimate-shortcut">Search Is the Ultimate Shortcut###</h3>

<p>Back in 2010, Groundwire found that search engines referred 55% of traffic to the nonprofit websites in their study. While we can’t do a direct comparison since the sites in question aren’t the same, I feel comfortable making the blanket statement that the trend is toward more traffic coming from search.</p>

<p>Here are the mean / median numbers since 2011:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/benchmark1.png" alt="benchmark1.png" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 47.06% / 43.97%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 48.12% / 50.12%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 52.99% / 54.02%</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>So far in 2014, those numbers have increased to 55% (mean) / 60% (median).</p>

<p>That means, of course, that traffic from the other two legs of the standard triumvirate have dropped:</p>

<p><img src="http://thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/benchmark2.png" alt="benchmark2.png" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 22.04% / 22.13%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 23.08% / 20.28%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 18.67% / 17.00%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2014 (to date): 16.18% / 13.98%</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="http://www.thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/benchmark3.png" alt="benchmark3.png" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 28.87% / 24.76%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 26.81% / 20.75%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 25.36% / 21.42%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2014 (to date): 25.82% / 19.75%</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Essentially, the best home page ever created will not solve your problems, as your users are more and more likely to turn to search first to find what they’re looking for. Your information architecture <strong>must</strong> take into account the fact that the first page your visitors encounter may be deep in your website.</p>

<p>User Experience starts in the first place your users experience you. You can use your data to make some assumptions about where that’s mostly likely to happen and optimize the top landing pages, but, more and more, you need to worry about every piece of content on your site.</p>

<h3 id="stop-wondering-if-mobile-is-important-right-now">Stop Wondering if Mobile Is Important Right Now###</h3>

<p>It is. Groundwire found that in 2010, the median number of mobile visitors to the sites in their study was just 1%. That’s changed over the past few years. Looking just at mobile phones (not tablets), you can see the surge:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/benchmark4.png" alt="benchmark4.png" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 5.70% / 4.97%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 7.68% / 7.67%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 12.84% / 12.04%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2014 (to date): 18.68% / 17.45%</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve seen the argument made that mobile doesn’t require your attention quite yet because it still represents, according to this data, just 1 in 5 visits.</p>

<p><strong>Our suggestion would be to get ahead of the curve instead of fighting to catch up</strong>. The growth in mobile traffic is having an obvious impact on the most basic measures of engagement.</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <td></td>
    <td>Mean</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Median</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Year</td>
    <td>Bounce Rate</td>
    <td>Time per Session</td>
    <td>Pages per Session</td>
    <td>Bounce Rate</td>
    <td>Time per Session</td>
    <td>Pages per Session</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2011</td>
    <td>62.30%</td>
    <td>2:04</td>
    <td>2.30</td>
    <td>67.07%</td>
    <td>1:57</td>
    <td>2.09</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2012</td>
    <td>66.17%</td>
    <td>1:58</td>
    <td>2.06</td>
    <td>67.20%</td>
    <td>1:56</td>
    <td>1.89</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2013</td>
    <td>70.48%</td>
    <td>1:54</td>
    <td>1.87</td>
    <td>70.10%</td>
    <td>1:39</td>
    <td>1.84</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p><em>[I’ve excluded 2014 because I haven’t cleaned out the data from sites that have gone through a responsive redesign. This isn’t meant to be a marketing piece, but I can tell you that redesigning for mobile can have a significant impact.]</em></p>

<p>My suspicion is that as people grow more comfortable using their smartphones to browse the Internet, visiting brands that have implemented a mobile strategy, they’re less likely to put up with sites that don’t work as well as they expect in their mobile browsers.</p>

<p>By structuring your content properly, you can create ways to put the content mobile users are most interested in front and center. If nothing else, you should take the time to understand what mobile visitors are doing on your site as a first step.</p>

<h3 id="loyalty-is-hard-to-come-by-or-even-define">Loyalty Is Hard to Come By (or Even Define)###</h3>

<p>Perhaps, given the growth in search and mobile traffic, it’s no surprise that the percentage of “New” visitors has increased over the years:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/benchmark5.png" alt="benchmark5.png" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 65.65% / 66.01%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 70.34% / 70.13%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 74.35% / 75.00%</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>On the flip side, “Loyal” visitors (defined as those with at least three visits in the period under review) have crashed:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.thinkshout.com/assets/images/blog/benchmark6.png" alt="benchmark6.png" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 20.86% / 19.00%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 15.64% / 15.66%</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 12.16% / 12.26%</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>And those numbers aren’t just relative percentage drops, caused by increases in other types of traffic, because the real numbers have dropped as well:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2011: 44,734 / 33,894</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2012: 43,076 / 29,989</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>2013: 37,757 / 22,781</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’m fairly confident, given the scale of the data, that this isn’t simply because people are getting better at clearing their cookies regularly – there’s wide variation in estimates, much of it from <a href="http://www.mnn.com/green-tech/computers/stories/americans-care-about-online-privacy-but-are-they-doing-anything-about">surveys of user behavior</a>, rather than <a href="http://www.kaushik.net/avinash/web-analytics-visitor-tracking-cookies/">actual data</a> – or <a href="http://www.elie.net/blog/privacy/19-of-users-use-their-browser-private-mode#.VAEKNWTt9ck">browsing the web incognito</a>. Those technologies have been around for years, and I doubt even Mr. Snowden has had that much of an impact on people’s everyday habits. (But I’m willing to be convinced otherwise.)</p>

<p>This loss could also be reflective of device fragmentation. Google and others are <a href="http://searchenginewatch.com/article/2280159/How-to-Use-the-Google-Analytics-New-vs-Returning-Report">working on ways to track users across the many devices they use</a>, but right now, if somebody visits you on August 14th on their laptop, comes back on September 9th on their tablet, and then again on October 21st on their phone, they would be classified as three different New users. As we see mobile traffic grow, it may mean that right now, we don’t have an accurate way to track visitor loyalty.</p>

<p>Perhaps some of that loyalty is being transferred elsewhere, however, from the website to social spaces, third party donation pages, or even mobile apps. In that case, the better sites are at converting website visitors into these different kinds of traffic, the less relevant the website will become to them.</p>

<p>Rare is the constituent who comes once a year to donate. Engagement, even within a multi-channel strategy, has to strike a balance between assuming that visitors will find continued value from the resources we make available on the web and moving new visitors to spaces where they’re more likely to continue to interact with us and each other.</p>

<p>In any case, if visitors <strong><em>are</em></strong> increasingly less likely to return to nonprofit websites, we need to rethink some of our engagement strategies. If they’re turning elsewhere because they aren’t finding what they want, when they want it, we’ve got some serious work to do.</p>

<h3 id="interested-in-helping-out">Interested in Helping Out?###</h3>

<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/a/thinkshout.com/spreadsheets/d/1xl8p1VKx4i6uG3kqmHmNdS6s4B6g2kmPIl9sKAtjHwA/edit#gid=0">I’ve made the spreadsheet with the cleaned data for 2011-2013 publicly available</a>. We hope you’ll check it out and add insights of your own!</p>

<p>But beyond using it as a tool to inform your own website, we could use your help. What other data should we track and share? What do you want to know?</p>

<p>And more importantly, are you willing to share your own?</p>

<p>If you’d like to work with us on a template that can be used to collect data from other nonprofits, just let me know. We’ll keep the org-by-org breakdown anonymous. Once we reach an arbitrarily large threshold  – 100,000,000 pageviews? – we can do some follow-up work.</p>

<p>Lev Tsypin, ThinkShout’s Director of Engineering, has suggested that we could go so far as to set up a Google form that feeds an anonymized spreadsheet. We could then make that data available via JSON, for further manipulation.</p>

<p>In the end, I believe that the more we aggregate and share, the better we’ll identify the problem areas we need to focus on as a community.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/09/nonprofit-website-benchmarks/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2014/09/nonprofit-website-benchmarks/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
