<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ThinkShout</title>
    <description>ThinkShout - We provide web strategy and open source technology to forward-thinking organizations.</description>
    <link>https://thinkshout.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/category/interns/rss.xml/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    
      <item>
  <title>Wrapping up ThinkShout Cares</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>It’s September – school is starting up, summer is winding down, and our ThinkShout Cares campaign has come to a close.</p>

<p>But in truth, it’s just the beginning.</p>

<p>Like many good ideas, this one was born over a round of beers at a conference last spring. Our new t-shirt designs, which focused on diversity and inclusion in response to the current political climate, were a huge hit. So, I joked, why not sell them year round? It’s one thing to get free swag at a conference, it’s entirely another to buy something on your own time and dime. Then someone else suggested to have all proceeds benefit a nonprofit, so the incentive for making a purchase goes well beyond just getting a cool shirt. Now this was getting interesting, but we still had a major obstacle: who would design the shirts, build the website, run the campaign, and fulfill the orders?</p>

<p>This last piece of the puzzle fell into place when we brought on our incredible class of interns, two of them from the <a href="http://emergingleadersinternship.org/">Emerging Leaders Internship program</a>. The ThinkShout Cares Campaign gave them experience in all aspects of a project, from designing the shirts to fulfilling orders. We chose <a href="http://pearmentor.org/">p:ear</a>, an incredible organization right in our neighborhood who creatively mentors homeless youth, as our partner and beneficiary.</p>

<p>We like to say that ThinkShout is a platform for good. It’s why we exclusively partner with mission-driven organizations. It’s why we’re a <a href="https://www.bcorporation.net/community/thinkshout-inc">B-Corp</a> and signatories to the <a href="http://techtownportland.com/pledge/">Tech Town Diversity Pledge</a>. It’s a driving force behind our growth. The ThinkShout Cares campaign is one example of how a business can do good that we’re all proud of. Our interns gained valuable experience and p:ear received a modest donation.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/ts-cares-group.jpg" alt="TS Cares Group" /></p>

<p>As for the ThinkShout team? Well, we can say with absolute certainty that this project was a bright spot in a summer that sorely needed one. It’s not a bad story to share, either!</p>

<h2 id="the-interns">The Interns</h2>

<p>ThinkShout hired three interns from the Emerging Leadership Internship program (ELI). This program connects students from underrepresented communities to businesses in Portland. We were thrilled to welcome <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/coding-for-good/">Myisha</a>, <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/thinkshout-cares-and-so-can-you/">Katrina</a>, and <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/designing-for-a-cause/">Alejandro</a> to our team.</p>

<p>These individuals were immediately thrown into work that involved technologies, platforms, and deliverables that had previously never crossed their paths. It was a situation that, for many of us, would cause great stress and anxiety; and they faced it with great aplomb.</p>

<p>While Myisha, Katrina, and Alejandro’s time at ThinkShout was temporary, their impact on our team has been permanent. They injected an energy to our office; and their humor and warmth has been missed since they departed to start school again in their respective locations. But we’ll be following along in their journeys to see all the wonderful things they do – because their time at ThinkShout was just the beginning!</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/interns.png" alt="ThinkShout interns" /></p>

<h2 id="about-pear">About p:ear</h2>

<p>ThinkShout has had an ongoing relationship with p:ear for some time now, including a pro bono project to help with their online engagement. We believe in their mission; that in giving an individual a purpose, respect, and a safe space in which to develop skills and talents, they can thrive and contribute back to society in meaningful ways.</p>

<p>At the start of this project, our interns met with p:ear students to brainstorm ideas for a t-shirt design for the campaign. It was a great opportunity to engage and put them in direct contact with the core of what p:ear is about: helping homeless youth thrive and succeed. In the end we created two designs that represented the heart and soul of this campaign.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/pear-summer.png" alt="Summer shirt designs" /></p>

<p><strong>We ended up raising $1,000 for p:ear!</strong> Money that will go towards art supplies, the barista school, and daily meals served at their facility.</p>

<h2 id="the-future-of-thinkshout-cares">The Future of ThinkShout Cares</h2>

<p>We embarked on this journey hoping to provide something of value to everyone involved: our interns would have truly meaningful work and gain valuable experience; p:ear would receive additional funding in the summer months – a time notoriously difficult for fundraising; and the ThinkShout team would learn from, and be inspired by, our partners.</p>

<p>What we ended up with was a living, breathing campaign that we see a future in, and we hope to revive ThinkShout Cares again to benefit another local organization impacting the community in which we work in and live.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/09/thinkshout-cares-wrap-up/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/09/thinkshout-cares-wrap-up/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Coding for Good</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Ever since I started coding, I’ve wanted to create a product that would make a difference. I wanted to contribute something good to society that would make someone else’s future better.</p>

<p>This summer, I got to do that.</p>

<p>My journey started with the <a href="http://emergingleadersinternship.org/about">Emerging Leaders Internship Program</a> (ELI). ELI helps match interns from underrepresented communities with companies in Portland. I was selected as a finalist in the program, and that is how I ended up at ThinkShout!</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/pear-Summer-Mission.png" alt="pear-Summer-Mission.png" /></p>

<p>I joined the ThinkShout team as a back-end development intern, my primary responsibility would be to build a website for their <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">summer campaign</a> alongside two other interns that worked on front-end development and design. Walking into a tech company can be intimidating; everyone looks and sounds so smart and talented. I was confident in my skills, but as an intern I worried I would not be able to deliver if I had to learn new languages or frameworks for the project. As I became immersed in the work however, that fear quickly vanished, and looking back I probably learned at least 15 new things every day, maybe even every hour.</p>

<p>The goal of the summer campaign site we were building was to raise money through t-shirt sales for a local nonprofit called <a href="http://pearmentor.org/">p:ear</a>. P:ear is an organization that creatively mentors homeless youth through education, art, recreation and job training. Their students designed one of the new shirts exclusively for this campaign, and our design intern, <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/designing-for-a-cause/">Alejandro</a>, designed the other new shirt!</p>

<p>For back-end development, the team decided to use Jekyll (an open source framework), a Shopify Storefront API plugin for the store, and an Amazon Web Services S3 to host the website. Jekyll was a simple solution for the project, since we were creating a one-page static website. Learning Jekyll was a little confusing since I had never worked with Ruby Gems or Liquid before, but their instructions are well documented so the initial site setup went smoothly.</p>

<p>My major roadblock in this project was working with the Shopify Storefront API. It is still in beta, so the problems I ran into were not well documented which led me to a lot of dead ends. Finally, I was able to get the products embedded by using Shopify’s “buy” button, which uses an access key to query in and display all products within a selected collection, and then automatically generates code, which can then be placed into a Javascript file.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/shopify-cart.png" alt="shopify-cart.png" /></p>

<p>Amazon Web Services provides a simple way to host a static site using an S3 Bucket. Essentially all you have to do is drop the files into the bucket and do some small configuration modifications to get the site hosted.</p>

<p>All the hoops I had to jump through to create the site ended up being great learning experiences. I had never worked with APIs before this project, and now I’m much more comfortable with them. I also got the chance to write a few Javascript functions, work with Github tickets, and gain experience working with an open source framework.</p>

<p>The experience of partnering with a nonprofit was also extremely valuable. Working with the students from p:ear really changed my perception of homelessness too. It taught me to look beyond what’s on the surface, and inspired me to pursue a project I had been thinking about for some time.</p>

<p>I had been wanting to create a website where black women could come together and discuss hair, hair products, and recommendations around both. But I also wanted it to be a space where we could figure out how to get unused/gently-used products to women who were homeless or from low-income households who could otherwise not afford them.</p>

<p class="center"><img src="/assets/images/blog/Project_C.png" alt="Project_C.png" /></p>

<p>While doing back-end work for the <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">p:ear campaign website</a>, I was simultaneously <a href="http://project-curls.org/">creating my own website</a> using open source software, Drupal. I had never used or even heard of Drupal before this summer and now I have completely developed a website using it, created a module, and have contributed a website to society that I believe will help with the distribution of hair care products for black women.</p>

<p>During my initial interview with ThinkShout, I was asked what I wanted to get out of this internship and I responded with, “experience.” It sounds broad, but having just completed my freshman year of college, I really didn’t know what area of technology would be best for me. Interning at ThinkShout has been a phenomenal experience, and as I continue to pursue a BS degree in Information and Computing Sciences, I hope to apply the professional and technical expertise I gained here to my studies and my next opportunity.</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/coding-for-good/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/coding-for-good/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Designing for a Cause</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>In college, I was told time after time that we should always first try working for a small company. Allegedly, this is because you experience all of the aspects that make up a company; in other words, you are not confined to your sole area of work.</p>

<p>For me, this turned out to be true. Now that it’s two months into my internship, I can confirm that I learned something about everything from web design, to coding, to public speaking while working on <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">ThinkShout Cares</a>. This internship has been an amazing experience. I am not exaggerating when I say that what I learned in two and a half months is equivalent to a whole year of school… assuming that everything I learned in school would actually be useful (I’m looking at you, Geology 101).</p>

<p>As the web designer for <a href="https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/thinkshout-cares-and-so-can-you/">ThinkShout Cares</a>, I was responsible for desinging a t-shirt and website that would fit nicely with <a href="http://pearmentor.org/">p:ear’s</a> message. You know, the shirt you <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/#shop">probably ordered by now</a>… right?  I really enjoy the design process. It is a world of its own where you’re always learning. I think it is one of those professions where you have to reinvent yourself or you might not stick with it. I love the challenge it provides, as it energizes me to continually venture out of my comfort zone. For this project, I was challenged to create a shirt that people would like enough to want to buy.</p>

<p class="full"><img src="/assets/images/blog/ts_cares_1.png" alt="ts_cares_1.png" /></p>

<p>When looking at the past ThinkShout shirts (I’ve heard they are pretty popular at conferences), I was amazed at the beautiful typography and messaging in each of them. <a href="https://thinkshout.com/team/jessica/">Jessica Tate</a> (my manager) is an avid typologist who, beyond being an amazing UX designer, makes reading delightful and easy by perfectly matching fonts. Knowing this, I knew that I should probably stay in my lane and do what I do best: illustration.</p>

<p>The designer has the same job as the writer: to communicate something. However, the beauty of design is that you have the power to communicate widely and personally. I completely understand that today, the web is a behemoth. Intended or not, the surplus of media we consume is enough to make us slam the laptop closed and walk away.</p>

<p>I had to split my time between designing a shirt and the website where we’d sell it. To achieve harmony, I was careful not to let them differ too much visually. The shirt and the website are authentic on their own; they are related, but they aren’t siblings. They’re more like cousins.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/ts_cares_2.png" alt="ts_cares_2.png" /></p>

<p>My goal was to create a serendipitous experience, something you did not expect, but you’re glad it happened. There are a few visual surprises throughout, connected by a theme. I chose the Universe as a theme because it is as beautiful as it is scary. I integrated hand drawn illustrations because there is an undoubtedly charismatic aspect about them. The more I drew, the more I discovered a sequence in my drawings. The top of the page marks the beginning of the sky. As you scroll down, you progress through the sky all the way down to the Portland skyline.</p>

<p>Sometimes, we need to slow down to appreciate web imagery; images often tells stories all on their own. When I was creating the t-shirt’s tropical pattern, I was unaware of how personal it was for me. In it, I was representing my home, a tropical town in Mexico on the coast of the Pacific Ocean where you see whales jump in the winter and you can find shells in the sand. For me, the beach is this place where you leave all of your worries behind and gorge yourself on the sun. It is one of the very few places where you actually stop and absorb the present. I am pretty content about how my design turned out. For me, the only thing missing there is a Ceviche. Too bad Ceviche isn’t aesthetically pleasing as the jumping whales.</p>

<p>I hope you enjoy the design as much as I do; it was such a fun process, and I’m especially happy that I was able to turn it into something that helps such an awesome organization like p:ear.</p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/designing-for-a-cause/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/designing-for-a-cause/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>ThinkShout Cares (and So Can You)</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>We’ve kept a pretty tight lid on this project all summer, but it’s finally time to unveil the focus of our 2017 Summer Internship program. Who better to tell you about it then the talented interns who built it?</p>

<p>You <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/06/the-2017-thinkshout-interns/">met Engineering intern Katrina Hirsch</a> last month on our blog. Now it’s her turn to tell you in her own words what we’ve been working on.</p>

<p><strong>Katrina Hirsch:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/blog/katrina.jpg" alt="katrina.jpg" class="left thirty" />It’s clear to me that ThinkShout is a company that cares deeply.</p>

<p>There is evidence of this not only in ThinkShout’s work, but also in the way that staff collectively interacts with our community. Staff want to be involved in creating positive change in the world, they want to give to organizations making a difference. Not because it’s an expectation, but because ThinkShout believes it’s the right thing to do. And so it was in the spirit of this sentiment that the idea for ThinkShout Cares was born.</p>

<p>After weeks of work, we are excited to announce the the idea is now reality. Say hello to <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">ThinkShout Cares</a>, a website designed, developed, and maintained by interns to raise funds for <a href="http://pearmentor.org/">p:ear</a>, a local non-profit whose mission is to mentor Portland’s homeless youth, by selling t-shirts designed by us and the students at p:ear.  And with 100% of the proceeds benefiting p:ear directly, it’s a win for everyone.</p>

<p><a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">ThinkShout Cares</a> was a project bestowed upon us summer interns as an opportunity to hone our skills (which are many and varied, including but not limited to writing, design, and coding) while also engage with the community. The idea was a simple one, really. We would design a t-shirt and then build a website where we’d sell it. All proceeds from our work would be donated to p:ear.</p>

<p>We began by taking a walk over to the p:ear headquarters, which is a mere three minutes from the ThinkShout office. None of us knew what to expect. What would this place look like? Who were these youth? What would we would learn in a single visit?</p>

<p>What we discovered was a vibrant space filled with intelligent, creative individuals. In many ways, they were just like us - uncertain of the future, eager to contribute, full of ambition and hope. We spent two hours talking and collaborating, which ultimately resulted in two very different, but equally awesome t-shirt designs.</p>

<p><a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/"><img src="/assets/images/blog/pear-summer.png" alt="pear-summer.png" class="center" /></a></p>

<p>Both designs are now for sale on <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">the e-commerce site that we built for this project.</a> Buy one, or maybe even a few. Proceeds from shirt sales will go towards funding mentorships at p:ear such as their barista program, bike repair shop, or outdoor recreation program. The hope being that in giving students a safe space to explore and learn about an area where they can apply themselves and contribute back to society. <a href="http://give.thinkshout.com/">Help us support p:ear</a> and keep the hope alive!</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 04:20:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/thinkshout-cares-and-so-can-you/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2017/08/thinkshout-cares-and-so-can-you/</guid>
</item>

    
      <item>
  <title>Sprinting on Entity Registration</title>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>We started hosting monthly sprints in order to pool our resources and give back to the open source community. We’re committed to maintaining our contributions that Drupal users rely upon - heck, we rely on them, too - and we owe it to this community to keep improving upon them. Not only that, but our own internal community here at ThinkShout grows as a result. There’s a camaraderie that develops when we all rally behind one cause, and it shows after every sprint in the way we collaborate on our projects.</p>

<p>This month, we focused on one of our most widely-adopted Drupal modules: <a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/registration">Entity Registration</a>.</p>

<p>There are nearly 10,000 sites currently using the Entity Registration module to power event signups. The module is supported by an active group of 43 developers who have contributed over 500 commits to the project. If you registered for a DrupalCon prior to this year, you’ve probably used this module. It’s been the canonical registration tool in Drupal because of the balance it strikes between ease of use and flexibility. We’ve built everything from simple signup forms for small, free events, to complex paid event registration workflows with tens of thousands of registrants.</p>

<p>The sprint resulted in a much-needed release of the Entity Registration module: <a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/2544986">7.x-1.5</a>. We knocked out a chunk of issues, added a bunch of nifty new features, and paved the way for some even <em>bigger</em> new features. Additionally, we made our initial <a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/2543160">port of Registration to Drupal 8</a> on a completely different branch.</p>

<p>What’s more, we had our interns on hand to participate in their very first sprint! <a href="http://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/06/meet-the-interns/">Daniel</a> even managed to make eight commits to Entity Registration. It was one of the most exciting Thursdays we’d had in a while. And that’s saying something, since bowtie Thursdays are pretty epic.</p>

<p>For this sprint, we broke into three teams. Team one focused on resolving the highest priority items in the issue queue, team two worked on building out a roadmap for upcoming features in the 2.x release, and team three began working on the D8 port.</p>

<p>Team one resolved over twenty issues in the queue and triaged nearly double that. I sat down with developers Gabe Carleton-Barnes, Jaymz Rhime, and Greg Boggs to discuss this latest sprint in detail.</p>

<p><strong>Gabe, your team was responsible for tackling the issue queue. How did you and your team divide and conquer those tickets?</strong></p>

<p><strong>Gabe</strong>: We started with the most important issues, and items that were prioritized in the issue queue already. We distributed them among our team, reproduced the issues, and came up with solutions. We had a lot of newer ThinkShout folks working on the queue, and our interns were on hand as well to help. It was a great opportunity for them to to get in there and give some feedback to the community. We were able to also get feedback from the community about these issues, evaluated their proposed solutions, and if they made sense, we implemented them as part of the fix.</p>

<p><strong>What were some of those bigger fixes?</strong></p>

<p><strong>Gabe:</strong> One of the more noteworthy had to do with anonymous registrations and permissions. Each time you create an event, you can allow people to register in different  ways. Registration by email address is one way, so anonymous users can provide an email address and not necessarily need to log into the site. But in order to make that work, you had to allow anonymous users with a permission called “allowed to register other people.” It logically worked at the time, but it was a little confusing for people setting up the module for the first time. So we took that out, which also provides a bit of a security buffer so you don’t have a bunch of anonymous users signing up with several different emails.</p>

<p><strong>Let’s shift gears and talk about features. It sounds like there are some exciting changes in the works for the Entity Registration module.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Greg</strong>: We started the process of refactoring entity registration in a big way. I created a <a href="https://www.drupal.org/node/2543164">roadmap</a> for the 2.x release of the module, which is important because there are contributors active in the Drupal community that are contributing to our module. So if we’re going to commit large chunks of new features to the module, it’s important to describe those to the other active developers working on the module so they know what’s coming and can participate in those changes.</p>

<p><strong>Jaymz</strong>: We developed a plan for implementing the biggest new features, and we’ve made some headway in service of those new features. We’re hoping to have these features ready to roll out in a month or so.</p>

<p><strong>Greg</strong>: There are two big features we’re prioritizing right now. The first is making entity registration work with any kind of entity, which is important for Drupal sites that use more than just “users.” This is a massive change that will drastically affect how this form will work. Right now, only users can register for events. With this feature, any entity will be able to register, whether it’s a contact, and email, etcetera, which is going to give both site owners and event registrants more options for both managing and registering for events. The second is the implementation of multiple registrations on a single event registration form.</p>

<p><strong>Jaymz</strong>: Both of these are features that have sort of worked in the past, but needed some fine-tuning. So now we’re adding true support for both of them.</p>

<p><strong>Greg</strong>: So many people use this module, and many of them are new to Drupal, which means this module has a very active issue queue. One of my top priorities is to respond to these issues, which I did during the sprint, ensuring people knew where to go for more support, reviewed proposed solutions, and so on.</p>

<p><strong>Jaymz</strong>: We really appreciate the support from the community, and we owe a lot of this module’s success to their contributions. It takes a village sometimes, or in this case, a team sprint, and Entity Registration is proof of that.</p>

<p><em>There are a lot of exciting things in the works for Registration. We can’t thank the community enough for their support of this module, and we’re looking forward to bringing it to Drupal 8. In the mean time, we hope you’ll give 7.x-1.5 a whirl and let us know what you think! Be on the lookout for updates about our progress and the new features coming in the near future.</em></p>

]]>
  </description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <link>https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/entity-registration-sprint/</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thinkshout.com/blog/2015/08/entity-registration-sprint/</guid>
</item>

    

  </channel>
</rss>
